<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The world to come, or The mysterie of the resurrection opened: in a discourse at Burford in the county of Oxon, upon Acts 24.15. / By John Osborn, minister of the Gospel at Bampton in the bush. As also, in a conference between him and Richard Coppin of Westwell.</title>
            <author>Osborne, John, lover of the truth as it is in Jesus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 173 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90206</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O526</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E635_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206479</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865634</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865634</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117882</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90206)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117882)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 97:E635[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The world to come, or The mysterie of the resurrection opened: in a discourse at Burford in the county of Oxon, upon Acts 24.15. / By John Osborn, minister of the Gospel at Bampton in the bush. As also, in a conference between him and Richard Coppin of Westwell.</title>
                  <author>Osborne, John, lover of the truth as it is in Jesus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by James Moxon, and are to be sold by Henry Hood, at his shop in S. Dunstans Churchyard, in Fleetstreet. MDCLI. [1651]</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 7th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117882:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The World to Come, <hi>OR</hi> The <hi>Myſterie</hi> of the RESURRECTION <hi>OPENED:</hi> In a Diſcourſe at <hi>Burford</hi> in the County of <hi>Oxon,</hi> upon <hi>Acts</hi> 24. 15. <hi>By</hi> John Osborn, <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpel at</hi> Bampton <hi>in the Buſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As alſo, In a Conference between him and <hi>Richard Coppin</hi> of <hi>Weſtwell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>James Moxon,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Henry Hood,</hi> at his Shop in S. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Churchyard, in Fleetſtreet. MDCLI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:117882:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117882:2"/>
            <head>To all that love the Truth in Since-cerity, particularly in <hi>Burford,</hi> and parts Adjacent, <hi>Grace and Peace.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dearly Beloved in our Lord Jeſus,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N every Age Perſecution hath been the lot, not only of the Servants, but alſo of the Truths of Jeſus; So that we ſhould not think it ſtrange, that in our Times ſuch a generation of men is ſprung up</hi> (Libertines <hi>they call themſelves) who to advance their</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Abiezer Cop,</hi> in ſweet ſips of Spiritual wine.</note> 
               <hi>Maſter's kingdom, make it their buſineſs to reſiſt the Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The great Idol they worſhip, to which all their damnable Hereſies and Practiſes are ſubſervient, is</hi> Senſual Liberty: <hi>That this Goddeſs may be honoured with daylie acceſs of new Converts, and the old be for ever held from departing from her; their Religion (if I may call it Religion) is ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived, that all Motives, Inducements, and Means, tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the promoting of Holineſs, and ſuppreſſing of Ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, as Obſtacles lying in the way, are removed; and ſtrong Engagements laid upon her Worſhippers, to have her ſtill in Veneration. We ſhall inſtance only in ſome few, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteed of many wherewith their Writings abound; particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly a Book entituled</hi> Divine Teachings, <hi>Publiſhed</hi> by one Richard Coppin, <hi>Anno</hi> 1649. <hi>Leſt the Excellency of God ſhould gain Proſelytes to him, they affirm All things to be God</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Part 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note>; <hi>that the Fulneſs of God dwels in us</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Part 1. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note>; <hi>Deny his ſpecial Love</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">P. 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note>; <hi>Anger, Wrath against ſinners</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Part 3. <hi>c.</hi> 8.</note>, <hi>and Juſtice in puniſhing them for ſin</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Part 3. <hi>c.</hi> 14.</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Beauty of Holineſs may not affect, they ſpeak contemptuouſly of it</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Preamble,</note>. <hi>That the baſeneſs of ſin may not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert
<pb facs="tcp:117882:3"/>
them from their ungodly ways, they take away all ſin, denying any guilt on men by reaſon of it</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">P. 3. ch. 16.</note>; <hi>That they may not be dotoerred through fear of puniſhments, or encouraged by expectation of a reward, they affirm there is no Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, Judgement, Heaven, Life Eternal, Salvation, or Hell but in this life</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Part 3. c. 3, 4, 5, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>; <hi>That no man hath any cauſe to be troubled</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Part 3 c. 24.</note>. <hi>And to prevent Tryal of their Doctrines by the Scripture, they vilifie it, and the Pen-men thereof; ſaying, the Prophets and Apoſtles knew nothing of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">p. 1. c. 12.</note>; <hi>calling it but a Dead</hi> Letrer, <hi>and darkning and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting it with Myſtical and Allogorical Interpretations. And that there may be no way left for better Information, they diſgrace the faithful Diſponſer; of the Goſpel</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">p. 1. c. 12.</note>; <hi>boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of glorious Diſcoveries, and clear Revelations, more curious and excellent Notions, and higher Attainments then others have</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">p. 1. c. 12.</note>; <hi>as if to them were committed the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of God: Which they endeavour to fasten upon their Hearers, by pretenſe of extraordinary zeal for God, and love to their peace and welfare. Laſtly, they contemn the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, Exerciſes of Religion, affirming a ſtate of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection here without them</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">p. 3. c. 29.</note>. <hi>Theſe and ſuch like, are the ways wherein they walk; ſo derogatory to Gods glory, and deſtructive to the ſouls of men that they ſhould be abhorred and oppoſed by all that love the Truth: Upon this account I have contributed my Aſſiſtance for the clearing of this Principle, the</hi> Reſurrection of the Dead; <hi>that you may be ſtrengehned, and hold fast the form of ſound words which ye have received. I have this only to add,</hi> Beloved, Believe <note place="margin">1 Iohn 4. 1.</note> not every ſpirit, but try the ſpirits: And if there come any unto you, and bring not this doctrine; receive him not into <note place="margin">2 Iohn 10. 11.</note> your houſe, neither bid him God ſpeed. <hi>If the Lord make the Diſcourſe inſtrumental for Conviction or Confirmation of any, I have my reward; which is the Prayer of</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your ſervant in the Goſpel of Christ.
John Osborne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117882:3"/>
            <head>The World to Come, OR The <hi>Myſterie</hi> of the RESURRECTION;</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>ACTS XXIIII. XV.</bibl>
               <q>And have hope towards God, which they themſelves alſo allow, that there ſhall be a reſurrection of the dead, both of the juſt and unjuſt.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E ſhould not marvel that there are Hereſics, for they are fore-told; or that ſo many are ſubverted by them: God therefore permits them that our faith may be tryed: <hi>There muſt be Hereſies among you, that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 19.</note> 
               <hi>they which are approved, may be be made manifeſt among you.</hi> The Envious man is diligent to ſow his Tares among God's Wheat; the carnal mind enmity againſt God, ready to forgo Truth, and embrace Error;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117882:4"/>
and the wiſe God for holy ends will have it for Hence it follows Hereſies muſt be. We do not wonder that diſeaſes are in the world, or that they are ſo catching and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive where they come; they are ſo common, and mens bodies ſo apt to be tainted, there is no ground of admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: They are then too vain and inconſiderate, who either marvel or are oftended that this main Article of our Faith, the Resurrection of the Dead, is queſtioned by ſome, and oppugned by others in theſe days of light, wherein knowledge ſo much abounds. It is for the tryal of our faith, that it might be found unto praiſe and glory, and honour, at the appearing of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now that you may not be as children, toſſed too and fro, but ſtrong in the faith, grounded and ſetled; I have deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined (by Gods aſſiſtance) to clear out this Fundamental points; therefore I beſeech you open your ears and hearts, while on theſe words of <hi>Paul</hi> I ſhall pour out my Meditations: The Lord make my Doctrine drop as the rain, and my Speech diſtil as the dew; as the rain upon the tender Herb, and as the ſhowers upon the graſs.</p>
            <p>The words are a part of <hi>Paul</hi>'s Apologie, to that ſtarcht ſpeech of <hi>Tertullus</hi> at <hi>Ceſarea</hi> before <hi>Felix</hi> the Governor: having cleared himſelf from ſome Miſpriſions, as to ſedition, he comes to a confeſſion of his Faith, <hi>v.</hi> 14. <hi>But this I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that after the way which they call Hereſie, ſo worſhip I the God of my Fathers; believing all things which are written in the Law and the Prophets:</hi> and ſo <hi>v.</hi> 15. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends to this particular of the Reſurrection, as a Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental point; the well laying or razing whereof, is the eſtabliſhment or downfal of the whole Fabrick of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> profeſſeth here his hope of the Reſurrection, which is further amplified; Firſt, by the efficient, God. Secondly, by the time of it, it is to come; it could not elſe be the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of his hope. Thirdly, by the ſubject matter, the dead; diſtinguiſhed into good and bad, juſt and unjuſt. Fourthly,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117882:4"/>
the conſent of his Adverſaries, which they themſelves alſo allow. Before we proceed, we muſt clear it out to be not a Spiritual but Bodily Reſurrection, not of the Soul, but of the Body; when the Body which by death faileth to the earth, is raiſed up again and quickned by the Soul; this is a ſecond conjunction or re-union after ſeparation, a ſecond marriage after divorce: and this appears from hence, Firſt, That it is ſaid to be the object of his hope, and ſo to come; for the ſpiritual he had already. Secondly, It is of juſt and unjuſt; the ſpiritual admits no ſuch diſtinction of perſons, all are juſt who are partakers thereof.</p>
            <p>It is ſomtimes expreſſed by living and awaking, and here by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to ariſe, the ſame in ſenſe with <hi>reſurgo,</hi> to riſe up again; as when a man having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a fall, ariſeth again; <hi>iterum enim ſurgendo reſurgere dicitur</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Tertul, de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur. carnis.</note>, the ſubject of the reſurrection is the ſame that falls; that which ariſeth, muſt firſt be down. The ſoul being immortal, cannot be ſuppoſed to dy, and therefore not aſhirmed to ariſe; therefore our bodies only are meant here: as in and by death there is a ſeparation of ſoul and body, a reſolution of the body into elements, and a disjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of them after this reſolution; ſo in the reſurrection, a gathering of thoſe elements into which our bodies are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, the forming of our bodies out of them, and anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them by a perpetual and indiſſoluble union with the ſoul.</p>
            <p>Now whereas the reſurrection of the body is either par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, of ſome men more eſpecially, as the ſon of the wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of <hi>Zarephath,</hi> and others; or general and common to all; the latter we ſpeak to; for it is in the Text, of the juſt and unjuſt.</p>
            <p>We ſhall firſt give you the proof of it, that there ſhall be ſuch a reſurrection; afterwards deſcend to the Explication of it; and laſtly to Application.</p>
            <p>Firſt of the verity of it; this cannot be diſcovered by natural light, or demonſtrated by Phyloſophical Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Et ut carnis reſurrectio ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getur, de una omnium Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la ſumitur.</hi> Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> praeſer. adver<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> haere.</note>;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117882:5"/>
to Phyloſophers it ſeems ſtrange, hard to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, yea ridiculous; therefore they encouncer <hi>Paul, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he preached unto him Jeſus, and the Reſurrection</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Acts 17. 18.</note>; and ſome mocked <note n="d" place="margin">Acts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 3.</note>, and <hi>Feſtus</hi> for this judges <hi>Paul</hi> mad <note n="e" place="margin">Acts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>; and no wonder, for the power by which we are raiſed and manner how, is ſupernatural, and the principles thereof not of themſelves obvious to the natural minde, but only to faith; which is the <hi>evidence of things not ſeen</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Heb 11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>: therefore faith <hi>Tertullian, Fiducia Chriſtianorum reſurrectio <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. caruis.</note>; The reſurrection of the dead is the faith of Chriſtians. For this therefore we muſt repair to Scripture, which affords plain aſſertions and concluding reaſons. For the firſt, among others theſe are remarkable that of <hi>David, I ſhall be ſatisfied when I awake with thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 17. 15.</note>; of his awaking out of the duſt, when he ſhould bear the Image of the heavenly. We have alſo Gods promiſe in <hi>Iſaiah, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dead ſhall live, together with my dead body ſhall they ariſe; awake and ſing ye that dwell in the duſt: for thy dew is as the dew of herbs, and the earth ſhall cast out the dead.</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Iſa. 26. 19</note> And again in <hi>Daniel, Many of them that ſleep in the duſt of the earth ſhall awake, ſome to everlaſting life, and ſome to ſhame and everlaſting contempt</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Dan. 12. 2.</note>. Parallel to this is that of cur Saviour, <hi>Marvel not at this; for the hour is coming, in the which all that are in the grave ſhall hear his voice, and ſhall come forth, they that have done good, unto the reſurrection of life; and they that have done evil, unto the reſurrection of damnation</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Ioh. 5. 28, 29</note>. And as Chriſt promiſeth, ſo <hi>Martha</hi> believeth a general reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>I know that he ſhall riſe agnin in the reſurrection at</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn 11. 24.</note> 
               <hi>the laſt day:</hi> This <hi>Paul</hi> affirms to be the <hi>hope of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe made of God unto the Fathers: Unto which</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>our twelve Tribes inſtantly ſerving God day and night, hope to come. Why ſhould it be thought a thing incredible with you, that God ſhould raiſe the dead</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">Acts 26, 6, 7, 8.</note>? The queſtion imports the credibility and inſallibility of it: it hath not reference (as I ſuppoſe) only to the reſurrection of Chriſt, but to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117882:5"/>
others alſo; or if Chriſt be here intended, the other may be hence inferred, as we ſhall clear in the reaſons.</p>
            <p>This Doctrine the Apoſtles taught, and for it the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers perſecute them; <hi>Being grieved that they taught the People, and preached through Jeſus the Reſureection from the dead</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Acts 4. 2.</note>. This alſo <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifies: <hi>For if we believe that Jeſus dyed and roſe again, even ſo them alſo which ſleep in Jeſus will God bring with him</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">1 Theſ. 4. 14.</note>. Compare <hi>v. 16. The dead in Chriſt ſhall riſe firſt.</hi> This muſt of neceſſity be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of the Reſurrection of the Body from natural death, not of the ſoul from ſin or ignorance as ſome vainly ſuppoſe; becauſe ſuch as the death or ſleep mentioned here is, ſuch is the riſing; But the ſleep, and death ſpecified, is not of ignorance, or ſin; becauſe it is ſuch a ſleep as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows a mans converſion, and the revelation of God in the ſoul, and is conſiſtent with communion and fellowſhip with Jeſus Chriſt; for they are ſaid to ſleep in Jeſus, and to be dead in Chriſt; <hi>v.</hi> 16. But a ſtate of Spiritual death and ignorance is inconſiſtent with communion with Jeſus Chriſt <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 1. compared with <hi>v. 12. You hath he quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned who were dead in treſpaſſes and ſins.</hi> Of whom <hi>v.</hi> 12. he ſayes <hi>At that time ye were without Chriſt.</hi> The ſame Doctrine is delivered in <hi>Phil. 3. 21. Who ſhall change our vile body, that it may be faſhioned like unto his Glorious body,</hi> &amp;c. The Libertines impudently affirm, it muſt be interpreted of deliverance from a ſtate of ignorance and corruption; they mean, when it is manifeſted to a man, that ſin is taken away; for (ſay they) it is onely ſin that makes the body vile: But this cannot ſtand, becauſe it is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of thoſe who were before this Spiritually riſen had the evidence of the Spirit in their hearts. <hi>Chap. 1. 29. Unto you it is given in the behalf of Chriſt, not onely to believe on him, but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake.</hi> Such as did <hi>worſhip God in the Spirit, and rejoyced in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> and had no confidence in the fleſh <note n="p" place="margin">Phil. 3. 3.</note>, ſuch as were after a ſort perfect: <hi>v. 15. Whoſe converſation was in Heaven</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Phil. 3. 20.</note>, from whence
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117882:6"/>
they did expect Chriſt to change their vile body, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This was not yet done; beſides, it is affirmed of the body, which is not the proper ſubject of ſuch a Reſurrection from ignorance, as they pretend; And our vile body ſhall be faſhioned like unto Chriſts body; but that as we ſhall hereafter prove, was raiſed properly from a natural death to a natural life.</p>
            <p>This is laid down as a Principle of the Doctrine of Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 3. which cannot with any ſhew of Reaſon be interpreted of any other then a corporall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection; having ſpoken of the Reſurrection of the Soul from a ſtate of ſin and ignorance, <hi>v.</hi> 1. where he menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Repentance from dead works, and faith towards God; It cannot be imagined that in ſo ſhort and pithy an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count as this is, he ſhould repeat the ſame again in other words; and this will be yet more clear, if we compare this paſſage with the fact and Faith of the Martyrs; wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men received their dead raiſed to life again, and others were tortured, not accepting deliverance <note n="r" place="margin">Heb. 11. 35.</note>. this was done through Faith, <hi>v.</hi> 33. Therefore by ſuch to whom God was manifeſt, they were tortured and killed, for they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted not deliverance; What inducement? They expected a better Reſurrection; What in this life? No, for they had no deliverance; if after death, what Reſurrection could it be but of the body: Beſides 'tis ſaid, <hi>A better Reſurrection;</hi> in reference to their beſt condition in this life.</p>
            <p>And this is ſhewed unto <hi>John</hi> in Viſion, <hi>I ſaw</hi> (faith he) <hi>the dead ſmall and great, and the Sea gave up the dead which were in it, and death and the grave</hi> (as in the Marginal reading) <hi>delivered up the dead which were in them</hi> 
               <note n="s" place="margin">Apo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 20. 12, 13.</note>. This cannot be underſtood of any other then a bodily Reſurrection. For firſt, it is general, <hi>Of all both ſmall and great:</hi> Now all ſorts do not riſe Spiritually, ſome dy in their ſins. Secondly, after they ariſe, they ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and are brought to judgement; But thoſe who ariſe Spiritually, do not ſtand before God to be judged,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117882:6"/>
as ſome of theſe here are, to be <hi>caſt into the Lake of fire. v.</hi> 15. Thirdly, the dead here are ſaid to be in the <hi>Sea,</hi> and in the <hi>Grave;</hi> and by them delivered up. Fourthly, ſome of them are ſaid not to be written in <hi>the Book of Life;</hi> therefore it cannot be a Spiritual Reſurrection; for all thoſe who are ſo riſen, are written in the <hi>Book of Life: Chap.</hi> 3. 4, 5. And thoſe who are unclean, and work a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination, or make a lie; who attain not to the Spiritual Reſurrection, are of that number which are not written in <hi>the Lambs Book of Life. Chap. 21. 2, 7. Iſaiah 25. 8. Hoſ.</hi> 13. 14. With many other places might be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to evidence this Truth; but theſe may ſuffice for Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive teſtimonies; we ſhall now repair to Reaſon.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The ſeed of the woman ſhall break the Serpents</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>head</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">Gen. 3. 15.</note>. Which is thus interpreted by <hi>John, 1 Epiſt. Chap. 3. v.</hi> 8. For this purpoſe the <hi>Son of God was mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted, that he might deſtroy the works of the Divel</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">1 Ioh. 3. 8.</note>: And this is one of his works, for he is deſcribed as having the power of Death. So that either death muſt be deſtroyed, <note place="margin">Heb 2. 14.</note> and conſequently the dead riſe, or Chriſt muſt fail of his end in being manifeſted in the world.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God is the God of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 2.</note> of all the Faithful; a God in Covenant with them, there <note place="margin">Exod. 3. 6.</note> fore their dead bodies ſhall riſe; this our Saviour urged againſt the <hi>Sadduces</hi> in Vindication of the Reſurrection, oppugned and denyed by them; <hi>But as touching the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the dead, have you not read that which was ſpoken unto you by God; ſaying, I am the God of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, and the God of Iſaac, and the God of Jacob? God is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 22. 31, 32</note> 
               <hi>not the God of the dead, but of the living.</hi> With this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the people were poſſeſſed with aſtoniſhment, and the <hi>Sadduces</hi> put to ſilence; <hi>v.</hi> 33, 34. Whereas the Lord cals himſelf their God, many years after they were dead and rotten in their graves; it imports they muſt be alive to God, they all live to him. But that you may clearly ſee the force of this Argument, and wherein its ſtrength lies,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117882:7"/>
we muſt conceive; when God cals himſelf the God of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> he means a God in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with them; to give out his All-ſufficiency for their good, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 1. to be their <hi>Shield and exceeding great reward;</hi> removing all cauſe of fear, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. 1. particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly iniquity, <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 25, 26. (the Fountain whence all evils flow) and ſupplying them with all good, out of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite fulneſs, for this Covenant brings a bleſſing with it, <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 25. which Covenant is an everlaſting Covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 7. and made with him; not in reſpect of the Soul onely, but the body alſo; for elſe it were not a perfect Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant: Theſe things premiſed, I thus infer;</p>
            <p n="1">1. That therefore by reaſon of this, Covenant, he will never leave them or forſake them; but ſhould not the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> riſe, God ſhould in that reſpect leave and forſake them, and not be All-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to them; or their God in reſpect of their bodies; the very duſt of the bodies of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> is in Covenant with him; and therefore ſhall in time be raiſed up again.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Foraſmuch as ſin (the cauſe of death) is taken away, therefore death, the wages of ſin, ſhall de done away.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If the bodies of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhall not live, they are not perfectly bleſſed in Covenant with God; becauſe their bodies (one part of them) are not.</p>
            <p>And what hath been ſaid of <hi>Abraham,</hi> is applyable unto all the Saints; God is their God, and therefore their dead bodies live to him, are in Covenant with him, have ſin the occaſion of death done away; and ſo ſhall be raiſed again, to be made perfectly happy with him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third Reaſon we draw from <hi>Mat. 22. 30. In the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Reſurrection they neither marry nor are given in marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age; but are as the Angels of God in Heaven.</hi> Which is thus rendred by <hi>Mark. 12. 25. When they ſhall riſe from the dead, they ſhall neither marry, nor are given in marriage:</hi> To the ſame purpoſe <hi>Luke</hi> 20. 35. In this life, in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117882:7"/>
Reſurrection from ſin and ignorance, men marry, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are given in marriage; <hi>Marriage is honourable in all, and the bed undefiled; but Whoremongers and Adulterers God will judge</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">Heb. 13. 4.</note>. And again, <hi>Nevertheleſs to avoid For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, let every man have his own wife.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, here we are not as the Angels of God, therefore <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 4.</note> we expect another Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>Moreover, ſuch a Reſurrection is here affirmed and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 5.</note> proved by Chriſt, which the <hi>Sadduces</hi> denyed, but that was of the body after death; when the ſeven Brethren one after another, and the woman alſo were laid in the grave, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. 23, to 29. What's the reaſon why our Saviour leaves more clear teſtimonies of the Prophets, and urge this of <hi>Moſes?</hi> It may be anſwered, Chriſt brings not any teſtimony out of the Prophets, becauſe (though they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted them the writings of excellent men, and ſo read them, and heard them read in the Temple) yet they recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved no more then the five Books of <hi>Moſes</hi> as Authentick, and of Divine Inſpiration <note n="y" place="margin">Sixt. Senenſ. Biblioth. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voce Traditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note>: Beſides, they were wont to elude clear teſtimonies, as the <hi>Libertines</hi> now do; inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting them Allegorically, applying them to ſome other thing; and this proves the Reſurrection of the dead <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by conſequence: Nor is there any evident mention of the Reſurrection or the life to come in <hi>Moſes,</hi> it being contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the common expreſſions of life and death, reward, and puniſhments; for <hi>Moſes</hi> drift was by external and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral things, to lead that people to the conſideration of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Eternal.</p>
            <p>The Reſurrection of Chriſt: Thus the Apoſtle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 6.</note> If Chriſt be riſen, we ſhal riſe; But Chriſt is riſen, therefore we muſt alſo ariſe; <hi>If Chriſt be preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that he roſe from the dead, how ſay ſome among you that there is no Reſurrection of the dead? And if there be no Reſurrection, then is not Chriſt riſen</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 12,</note>. Now if we be dead with Chriſt, we believe that <hi>we ſhall alſo live with him</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 13.</note>; And to the <hi>Theſſalonians:</hi> If we believe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117882:8"/>
               <hi>that Jeſus died and roſe agatn, even ſo them alſo which ſleep in Jeſus, will God bring with him</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">1 Theſ. 4. 14.</note>. Nor was this the Doctrine of <hi>Paul</hi> onely, but of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets before him; as he affirmeth of himſelf, that he ſaid, <hi>No other things then thoſe which the Prophets and Moſes did ſay ſhould come; that Chriſt ſhould ſuffer and that he ſhould be the firſt that ſhould riſe from the dead</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Acts 26. 22, 23.</note>. If he be the firſt, then others muſt riſe after him; yea, and by vertue of his riſing; why elſe ſhould it be deferred till his Reſurrection? But how is Chriſts Reſurrection the cauſe and evidence of ours? The Apoſtle clears it from our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, which he expreſſeth in a figure or type of the old Law: <hi>Chriſt is riſen from the dead, and become the firſt fruits of them that ſiept</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor, 15. 20.</note>. The firſt fruits offered to God, ſanctifyed the reſt of the Crop; therefore, <hi>If the firſt fruits be holy ſo is the lump</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 11. 16.</note>; and they both have the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; Chriſt our firſt fruits is riſen: This ſhewes both the cauſe and order of our Reſurrection; we ſhall riſe alſo, and by him.</p>
            <p>To the ſame purpoſe in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, He is the Head of the body the Church the beginning, and the Firſt-born from the dead</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Col. 1. 18</note>. He as our Head riſes, then we the body muſt come after; he is the Beginning, then he hath an influence upon us; and in riſing gives us aſſurance we ſhall riſe alſo; he is the Firſt-born from the dead, or the Firſt-begotten of the dead <note n="f" place="margin">Revel. 1. 5.</note>, then his Brethren ſhall be remembred by him; he hath a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble portion, that he might take care of the Family; if he live, they ſhall live alſo.</p>
            <p>He roſe not as a private Perſon, or for himſelf alone; life was given him as an Head and Firſt-born to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate, that our emptineſs might be ſupplyed out of his Treaſury; it was in him not onely abundant, but redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant; it overflows; and therefore in his Reſurrection, he is termed a Prince and a Saviour: <hi>The God of our Fathers raiſed up Jeſus</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Acts 5. 30, 31.</note>, <hi>a Prince, and a Saviour:</hi> Or to be a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117882:8"/>
Prince and a Saviour to diſpenſe life unto his <hi>Subjects; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I live ye ſhall live alſo<hi rend="sup">h</hi>:</hi> And as his Perſonal Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection <note place="margin">Iohn 14. 19.</note> is a cauſe, ſo a pattern of ours; he roſe as a common perſon, and therefore he roſe with a multitude; many Saints roſe with him, and <hi>we ſaid to be raiſed up together with him</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Eph. 2. 6.</note>, this the Apoſtle further illuſtrates by a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of two contrary cauſes; <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> producing two contrary effects, death, and life; <hi>Since by man came death, by man came alſo the Reſurrection of the dead. For as in Adam all dy even ſo in Chriſt ſhall all be made alive.</hi> If <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 21, 22.</note> any demand, Why then are we not preſently raiſed, we are mortal and begin to dy even in our mothers womb? My anſwer is ready: Chriſt is the firſt fruits; both firſt fruits and lump are gathered; but firſt the firſt fruits, then the lump; Chriſt and they that are Chriſts, riſe to heavenly glory, but each in his order; firſt Chriſt, then they that are Chriſts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we ſhall be gathered, but in our time appointed of the Father. The Inference you ſee is clear; If Chriſt be riſen, then we ſhall riſe alſo; and after the ſame manner.</p>
            <p>How doth it appear that Chriſt is riſen bodily? May not <note place="margin">Queſt.</note> this be underſtood Spiritually and Myſtically, not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Literally; Figuratively and not Properly? Why ſo? What ſhould <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> hinder but that it is literally and properly to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the living again of that body of fleſh and bones that ſuffered, dyed, and was laid in the grave? What ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furdity will follow if we ſo conceive it? He roſe again the third day according to the Scriptures? Why ſhould we doubt, or wreſt them to another ſenſe, when no ill conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence can be urged in pretenſe thereof? And why elſe ſhould <hi>Paul</hi> name his dying and being buryed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 4. if it were another kind of life and riſing, then ſuch as is anſwerable to his death and lying in the Earth?</p>
            <p>And that we may not be faithleſs but believe, the Scriptures afford many convincing infallible Arguments in vindication of this Truth: Firſt his many apparitions, <hi>He was ſeen of Cophas, then of the twelve</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 5.</note> 
               <hi>After that he was
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117882:9"/>
ſeen of above five hundred Brethren at once</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">verſe 6.</note>. <hi>After that he was ſeen of James, then of all the Apoſtles</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">verſe 7.</note>. <hi>And laſt of all he was ſeen of me alſo</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">verſe 8.</note> ſaith Paul. <hi>Mark</hi> affirmes he was firſt ſeen of <hi>Mary Magdalen. John</hi> not onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports that, but their diſcourſe together <note n="p" place="margin">Mark 16. 9.</note>. Then of more women together <note n="q" place="margin">Ioh. 20. 14, 15, 16, 17.</note>; and ſaying, <hi>All Hail. And they came, and held him by the feet, and worſhipped him. v.</hi> 10. Then ſaid <hi>Jeſus</hi> unto them, be not afraid, go tell my Brethren, that they go into Galilee, and there ſhall they ſee me <note n="r" place="margin">Mar. 28. 9, 10.</note>. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he appeared in <hi>another form unto two of them</hi> (that is Diſciples) <hi>as they walked and went into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> 
               <note n="s" place="margin">Mar. 16. 12.</note>. <hi>While they communed together and reaſoned</hi> (ſaith Luke) <hi>Jeſus himſelf drew neer and went with them, but their eyes were holden that they ſhould not know him</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">Luke 24. 15, 16.</note>. They diſcourſe together, he preacheth unto them, and he adds; <hi>They drew nigh unto the Village whither they went, and he made as though he would have gone further</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">verſe 19, to 28.</note>. <hi>But they conſtrained him, ſaying, Abide with us, for it is to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards evening, and the day is far ſpent: and he went in to tarry with them. And it came to paſs, as he ſate at meat with them, he took bread, and bleſſed it, and brake, and gave to them. And their eyes were opened, and they knew him, and he vaniſhed out of their ſight</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">verſe 29, 30, 31, 32.</note>.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>the ſame day at Evening, When the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples were aſſembled for fear of the Jewes, came Jeſus and ſtood in the midſt of them, and ſaith unto them, Peace be unto you. And when he had ſo ſaid, he ſhewed unto them his hands, and his ſide: then were the Diſciples glad when they ſaw the Lord</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Ioh. 20. 19, 20.</note>. And ſaith <hi>Mark, He upbraid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them with their unbelief and hardneſs of heart, becauſe they believed not them which had ſeen him after he was riſen, Mark</hi> 16. 14. But <hi>Thomas</hi> was not with them, <hi>Ioh. 20. v.</hi> 24. He again appeared unto them when <hi>Thomas</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 20. 26.</note> was with them who becauſe he had raſhly ſaid, <hi>Except I ſhall ſee in his hands the print of the nails, and put my finger into the print of the nails, and thruſt my hand into
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117882:9"/>
his ſide, I will not believe; John</hi> 20. 25. therefore ſaith he to <hi>Thomas, Reach hither thy finger, and behold my kands: and reach hither thy hand, and thruſt it into my ſide; and be not faithleſs, but believing:</hi> v. 27.</p>
            <p>That this reſurrection is not only ſpiritual, appears from <hi>Luke 24. 39. Behold my hands and my feet, that it is my ſelf; Handle me, and ſee; for a ſpirit hath not fleſh and bones as ye ſee me have:</hi> And from <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 42, 43. for he eats of broyled fiſh, and an honey comb.</p>
            <p>Alſo the Sea of <hi>Tiberias,</hi> while they were a fiſhing, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſeth with them, works a miracle, eats bread and fiſh, <hi>John</hi> 21. 1, to 23.</p>
            <p>A fourth time to the Diſciples, on a mountain of <hi>Galilee, Mat.</hi> 28. 16. where they worſhip him, and receive a Commiſſion to baptize and preach to the Nations, <hi>ver.</hi> 17, to the end.</p>
            <p>Of theſe apparitiors (ſaith <hi>Luke) He ſhewed himſelf alive after his Paſſion, by many infallible proofs; being ſeen of them forty days, and ſpeaking of the things pertaining to the Kingdom of God,</hi> Acts 1. 3. He manifeſted himſelf to their eys, by his viſible preſence, ſtanding among them, walking with them, eating and drinking before them; to their ears, by audible words; to their hands, by touching of his fleſh: and that they might be ſure it was no deluſion, he opens their underſtandings <note n="z" place="margin">Luke 24. 45.</note>, works miracles, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers on them the holy Ghoſt, and the gift of working won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders <note n="a" place="margin">Mark 16. 17, 18.</note>.</p>
            <p>From Apparitions, let us come to Atteſtations; we have firſt the Teſtimony of Angels: <hi>He is not here, for he is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen as he ſaid; Come, ſee the place where the Lord lay:</hi> Matth. 28. 6. <hi>And go quickly, and tell his Diſciples that he is riſen from the dead.</hi> Verſ. 7. And in <hi>Mark, He is riſen, he is not here; Behold the place where they laid him,</hi> Mark 16. 6. <hi>But go your way, tell his Diſciples and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he goeth before you into Galilee, there ſhall ye ſee him as he ſaid unto you.</hi> In Luke, <hi>Why ſeek ye the living
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117882:10"/>
among the dead.</hi> Chap. 24. 5. Figuratively Spiritually this cannot be meant, but Properly and of a bodily Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; that which the women ſought, the Angels affirm to be riſen; what was crucified, what was laid in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher, what they came to embalm, what <hi>Mary</hi> thought had been taken away; <hi>John</hi> 20. 15. and that was the body of Jeſus.</p>
            <p>We have alſo the witneſs of the women <note n="b" place="margin">Luke 24. 10.</note>, who firſt ſaw him after his reſurrection, <hi>Mark</hi> 16. 10, 11. The two Diſciples, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. The ten Diſciples, <hi>verſ.</hi> 20, 25. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of <hi>Thomas, John</hi> 20. 27, 28. and therefore is <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias</hi> choſen with the eleven to be a witneſs hereof, <hi>Acts</hi> 1. 22, to the end. To this all the Apoſtles bear witneſs, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 31. and 5. 30, <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 2, 3. <hi>Rom. 10. 9. 1 Cor.</hi> 15. 4. 5, 11, 12, 15, 20. Laſtly, the Watchmen, enemies to Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 11, 12, 13, 14, 15. Having ſuch a cloud of witneſſes, why ſhould we doubt?</p>
            <p>Hereunto might be added Propheſies <hi>Pſal. 16. 10. Mark 9. 31. and</hi> 10. 34. and Figures aforegoing, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. 40. Signes accompanying, and effects following it; as the Earthquake, the glorious Apparition of Angels, filling the Keepers of the grave with terror and amazement; for they did ſhake, and became as dead men; <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 4. If the Reſurrection were ſpiritual, why not the Earthquake alſo, and the deſcent of the Angels? and if theſe were but in fancy, how is it they became as dead men?</p>
            <p>Let us next view the Sepulcher, the place where the Lord lay; <hi>Luke</hi> reports, when the women entred in, they found not the body, <hi>Chap.</hi> 24. 3. and the Angel ſaith, <hi>He is not here; Matth. 28. 6. Mark</hi> 16. 6. and they give the reaſon; <hi>For he is riſen: Matth. 28. 6. Mark 16. 6. and is gone into Galilee:</hi> Did he riſe in Spirit? Then he went in Spirit into <hi>Galilce.</hi> How impertinent is this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the occaſion, their ſeeking the body of the Lord? and how is this a reaſon why he could not be in the grave, He is riſen ſpiritually and myſtically, therefore his body is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117882:10"/>
not here? Can ſuch non-ſenſe (think you) be allowed the words of an Angel? If ſpiritual, how come the carnal Souldiers to know it? Beſides, to what purpoſe did they affirm his Diſciples came by night and ſtole him away? <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 13. Sure we are, he was bodily in the Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher. To this the <hi>Libertines</hi> themſelves (though ſufficiently impudent) will conſent. I demand, where is that body now? What is become of it? Is it annihilated? that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be; for it ſaw no corruption, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 31. In the grave it ſtayed not; He is not here: ſhew us where it is, and it ſufficeth. But this is beyond any revelation of theirs to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare: They muſt remain for ever ſilent in this point, or profeſs they cannot tell. That it was ſtolen away by the Diſciples, the ſuborned Watchmen ſaid, and that when they were aſleep, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 13, 14, 15. If they were awake, why did they ſuffer it? If when they were aſleep, how did they know it? but theſe men affirm they know not what; the body ſtole away they know not how: we can give a better account of it from the words of the Angels, It is riſen from the dead, and aſcended up into heaven, from whence he ſhall come again in like manner as he went up; <hi>to execute judgement upon all, to convince all that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly among them, of all their ungodly deeds which they have ungodly committed, and of all their hard ſpeeches which ungodly ſinners have ſpoken againſt him,</hi> Acts 1. 11. Jude 15.</p>
            <p>He is gone from the Sepulcher, but the Linnen clothes and Napkin are left behind; <hi>John</hi> 20. 5, 7. this and the rolling away of the ſtone, <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 2. to me are a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent proof of his bodily reſurrection.</p>
            <p>Next if we conſider his Aſcenſion into heaven, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be unſatisfied in his riſing from the earth. This is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported <hi>Acts</hi> 1. when he had continued forty days on earth among his Diſciples, he commanded them, being aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled together at <hi>Bethany</hi> (whither he had led them) to to wait for the promiſe of the Father; which was Baptiſm
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117882:11"/>
with the holy Ghoſt, which he then gave them aſſurance they ſhould receive: and having told them they ſhould <hi>be witneſſes to him in Jeruſalem, Judea, Samaria, and unto the utmost part of the earth: When he had ſpoken theſe things, while they beheld, he was taken up, and a Cloud re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him out of their ſight:</hi> verſ. 9. <hi>and while they lock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſtedfaſtly towards heaven as he went up, behold two men ſtood by them in white apparel,</hi> verſ. 10. <hi>which alſo ſaid, Ye men of Galitee, Why ſtand ye gazing up into heaven? This ſame Jeſus which is taken up from you into heaven ſhall ſo come in like manner as ye have ſeen him go into heaven,</hi> verſ. 11. What more plain then this? He went up bodily, and there continues; For the <hi>Heavens muſt receive him until the times of the reſtitution of all things; Acts</hi> 3. 21.</p>
            <p>We might alſo clear this point from the efficacy of his Reſurrection in thoſe that believe the diſpenſation of extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary gifts to the Church; the deſcent of the holy Ghoſt, Signes and Miracles wrought by thoſe that preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his Name: All which ſufficiently confirm and ſeal our Faith in his bodily Reſurrection. I ſhall add only one Argument more, and then touch upon ſome abſurdities in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred by the Apoſtle from the denyal of this point,</p>
            <p>Whatſoever manner of Reſurrection theſe Dreamers fancy, the Jews that ſlew him took it to be a bodily one, the quickning of his dead body; for <hi>the chief Prieſts and Phariſees came together unto Pilate, ſaying; Sir, We re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that that Deceiver ſaid whil ehe was yet alive, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter three days I will riſe again. Command therefore that the Sepulcher be made ſure until the third day, leſt his Diſciples come by night and ſteal him away; and ſay unto the people, He is riſen from the Dead; ſo the last Error ſhall be worſe then the firſt. Pilate ſaid, ye have a Watch, Go your way. make it as ſure as you can. So they went and made the Sepulcher ſure, ſealing the ſtone, and ſetting a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">c Mat. 27. 62, 63, 64, 65, 66.</note> 
               <hi>Watch.</hi> If it were a ſpiritual Reſurrection foretold, why did
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117882:11"/>
they fear, and uſe means to prevent the ſtealing of his body, in that they make this ſure by guarding, ſtopping, and ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Sepulcher? It is evident they underſtood it of the reſurrection of his body, and his Diſciples meant no other; why elſe ſhould <hi>they</hi> fear they would ſteal his body, and then give out he was riſen? and why elſe did they after his reſurrection aſſemble with the Elders, take counſel, give large money to the Souldiers, ſaying, <hi>Say ye his Diſciples came by night, and ſtole him away while we ſlept,</hi> Mat. 28. 12, 13, which they did accordingly? <hi>v.</hi> 15. Doubtleſs ſuch a reſurrection it was as they denyed; but this was bodily: This the Apoſtles preached, and this the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians believed. From the denyal whereof (among other) there ariſe theſe abſurdities, as <hi>Paul</hi> affirms; <hi>Then is our preaching vain,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 14, <hi>and your faith is alſo vain;</hi> v. 14. <hi>we are found falſe witneſſes of God;</hi> v. 15. <hi>Ye are yet in your ſins,</hi> v. 17. <hi>Then are they alſo which are fallen aſleep in Chriſt, are periſhed.</hi> v. 18.</p>
            <p>All which are inconſiſtent with the Chriſtian faith; therefore Chriſt is bodily and properly riſen from the dead. So much hath bin ſaid in proof of Chriſt's reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, I ſhould be aſtoniſhed at the unbelief of any, but that I am taught <hi>faith is the gift of God</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Eph. 2. 8.</note>; and the ſame power required to beget faith, as raiſed Chriſt from the dead <note n="e" place="margin">Eph. 1.</note>: and that the Diſciples themſelves (though it were foretold by Chriſt before his death) were not for a time ſo clear and ſtedfaſt. but dark and ſtaggering in this point: <hi>Luke 24. 21. We truſted that it had been he which ſhould have redeemed Iſrael; and beſide all this, to day is the third day ſince theſe things were done.</hi> Some of them, though they had heard from <hi>Mary, that he was alive and had been ſeen of her, believed not;</hi> Mark 16. 11. <hi>for as yet they knew not the Scripture, that he muſt riſe again from the dead;</hi> John 20. 9. <hi>but their words ſeemed unto them as idle tales, and they believed them not:</hi> Luke 24. 11. Yea two of them travelling to <hi>Emmaus,</hi> though cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117882:12"/>
women of their company had declared unto them that they had been at the Sepulcher, found not his body theres but had ſeen a Viſion of Angels, which ſaid that he was alive: and though two of them which had been with them, went the Sepulcher, and found it even ſo as the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men had ſaid, only they ſaw him not; notwithſtanding all this, they believed not: For which cauſe Chriſt appears un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them &amp; reproves them ſharply, <hi>O fools and ſlow of heart to believe all that the Prophets have ſpoken; Luke</hi> 24. 25. theſe went and told it to the reſidue; neither believed they them; <hi>Mark</hi> 16. 12, 13. Therefore Chriſt afterward appearing to them <hi>as they ſate at meat, upbraided them with their unbelief and hardneſs of heart, becauſe they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved not them which had ſeen him after he was riſen;</hi> Mark 16. 14. At this appearing <hi>they were terrified and affrighted, ſuppoſing that they had ſeen a ſpirit;</hi> Luke 24. 37. And <hi>Thomas</hi> (though it had been declared unto him by the reſt of the Apoſtles) reſolved with himſelf, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſeeing and feeling the print of the nails, and thruſting his hand into his ſide, not to believe; <hi>John</hi> 20. 25. No wonder then, if when we preach the Reſurrection of Chriſt, and of the dead by him, ſome wonder, others doubt, ſome oppoſe, others laugh, as if they had heard ſtrange incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ridiculous things to day.</p>
            <p>But how ſtrange ſoever it is to the natural man, it hath been an Article of Faith in all Ages ſince Chriſt; as might be proved by Fathers, and other Champions of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith, Councels Creeds, Hiſtories from Chriſt to our times. But we ſuppoſe it ſufficiently made out by what hath been ſpoken and written, as it were with a ſun-beam in the Scriptures, that he who runs may read it. We have been the more liberal in allowance of our time and pains upon this Theam, becauſe this is the firſt and chief foundation-ſtone upon which our reſurrection is founded, the main prop by which it is ſupported, the example unto which it is conformed, and the fountain whence it is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117882:12"/>
derived, and therefore the moſt eminent evidence by which it is cleared.</p>
            <p>We proceed to the Apoſtle's next Argument; the end <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 7.</note> of our Redemption, and the abſurd conſequent of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Doctrine: <hi>If in this life only we have hope in Chriſt, we are of all men moſt miſerable.</hi> The Argument may be formed thus (this being preſuppoſed, If there be no reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the dead, then Chriſtians have onely hope in this life) If in this life only Chriſtians have hope in Chriſt, then they are of all men moſt miſerable; But Chriſtians are not of all men moſt miſerable, Therefore they have not hope in Chriſt only in this life.</p>
            <p>The conſequence is clear, for of all men, they in this life are moſt ſubject to afflictions; <hi>Whom the Lord loveth, he chaſteneth, and ſcourgeth every ſon he receiveth: What ſon is he whom the Father chaſteneth not? But if ye be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb 12. 6, 7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>chaſtiſement, whereof all are partakers, then are ye baſtards, and not ſonst.</hi> They uſually have the bread of affliction given them to eat, and water of affliction to drink; yea waters of a full cup are wrung out to them, when others fare delictiouſly every day; their chain is made heavie, when others walk at liberty; they are brought low, when others are lifted up; their heaven is covered with darkneſs, clouds, and thick darkneſs, when others have clearneſs and ſerenity, the ſun continually ſhining in his brightneſs; their condition admits variety of revolutions, but theſe have no changes; therefore if there be no hope to them of a better ſtate in another world, they are of all men moſt miſerable. But the Chriſtian Faith and Scriptures makes them of all men moſt happy, yea, and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly them happy: Chriſt hath purchaſed, God promiſed, the Spirit ſealed better things to them then what other men have, or themſelves enjoy in this world; they are again and again pronounced bleſſed, nine times in ſo many verſes, <hi>Math.</hi> 5. 2, to 12. the manifold repetitions, and particular inſtances of their bleſſedneſs, notes the firmneſs and fulneſs
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117882:13"/>
of it; <hi>They are bleſſed with all ſpiritual bleſſings in the heavenly places in Chriſt,</hi> Eph. 1. 3. Freedom from all evil, fruition of all good; particularly, deliverance from the evil of death: Chriſt hath delivered them, <hi>who through fear of death, were all their life time ſubject to bondage;</hi> Heb. 2. 15. How are they delivered from death, or the fear of death, if ther bodies ſhall for ever remain under the power of it, and never be ſet at liberty? This all men deſire, ſith death is the King of Terrors, and the Saints hope for; <hi>we our ſelves groan within our ſelves, waiting for the Adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Redemption of our body,</hi> Rom. 8. 23. Juſt they are before, and God is manifeſt in them, yet they wait for the Redemption of the body, <hi>viz.</hi> from the grave, and thoſe evils they are incumbred with in the world: <hi>They ſhall hunger no more, neither thirſt any more, neither ſhall the ſun light on them, nor any heat;</hi> Rev. 7. 16. <hi>God ſhall wipe away all tears from their eys, there ſhall be no more death, neither ſorrow, nor crying, neither ſhall there be any more pain, for the former things are past away;</hi> Rev. 21. 4. Shall all this be in this life? Is all this in myſterie? If ſo, how is it fulfilled? Or, is it in death to the Saints? In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed there is no hunger, thirſt, heat, tears, ſorrow, crying, or pain; but yet they have not all promiſed, how in death is this accompliſhed, <hi>there ſhall be no death?</hi> But this is not all a Chriſtians hope, immunity from evils, there is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſe of reward to come; poſitive good, and that after death: Therefore (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>when thou makeſt a feast,</hi> (this command binds all our life long, while there is occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and opportunity of feaſting) <hi>call the poor, the maimed, the lame, the blind, and thou ſhalt be bleſſed; for they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not recompenſe thee, but thou ſhalt be recompenſed at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the juſt;</hi> Luke 14. 14. that this is not in this life, is manifeſt from that parallel, <hi>Heb. 11. 35. They</hi> (the Saints) <hi>were tortured, not accepting deliverance, that they might obtain a better reſurrection:</hi> and from <hi>Rev. 11. 18, and the Nations were angry, and thy wrath is come, and the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117882:13"/>
time of the dead that they ſhould be judged, and that thou ſhouldeſt give reward unto thy ſervants the Prophets, and to the Saints, and them that fear thy Name, ſmall and great.</hi> This is the promiſe mentioned, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 39. and perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>v.</hi> 40. which the Patriarchs received not: <hi>Theſe all ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving obtained a good report, through Faith, received not the promiſe; the Apoſtle ſpeaks of men dead long before, and dying in Faith, that they received not the promiſe:</hi> God being faithful, it muſt be received in due time; in ſoul they can not receive it in full after death; the time of receiving it, is when all are made perfect; <hi>God having pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided ſome better thing for us, that they without us ſhould not be made perfect:</hi> Of this perfection God will have all partakers together; and this perfection cannot be without the Reſurrection of the body; and this very thing is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly affirmed of <hi>Abel, Noah, Abraham, Sarah, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob; theſe all dyed in Faith, not having received the promiſes, but having ſeen them afar off, and were perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of them, and imbraced them, and confeſſed that they were Strangers and Pilgrims on the earth.</hi> While they lived, they received not the promiſes, but ſaw them at a diſtance, in reſpect of time and place; they looked not for them in that time or Country, for then and there they were Strangers and Pilgrims; and that we might not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain it to any one particular Country or more, they take the whole earth in, ſaying, that in it they were Strangers and Pilgrims; and hence the Apoſtle concludes, <hi>v 14. They that ſay ſuch things, declare plainly that they ſeek a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, What country?</hi> not an earthly; <hi>and truly, if they had been mindful of that country whence they came out, they might have had opportunity to have returned; but now they deſire a better country that is heavenly;</hi> v. 16. and this in the cloſe of this verſe he calls a City prepared of God: <hi>For God is not aſhamed to be called their God for he hath prepared for them a City;</hi> and this is not theirs only, but the inheritance of all Saints: <hi>Here we have no continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117882:14"/>
City, but we ſeek one to come. Chap.</hi> 13. 14. Which is expreſſed by life <hi>If we be dead with him, we ſhall alſo live with him. 2. Tim.</hi> 2. 11. Eternal and everlaſting life. <hi>The gift of God is eternal life Rom.</hi> 6. 23. <hi>This is the will of him that ſent me, that every one that ſeeth the Son and believeth on him, may have everlaſting life; and I will raiſe him up at the laſt day</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Ioh. 6. 40.</note>. If it be eternal and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting, and for the perfection of it require a raiſing up at the laſt day, how is it limitted to this life? And for his aſſurance, Chriſt tells him that he hath it already; <hi>Who ſo eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my blood, hath eternal life; and I will raiſe him up at the laſt day. v.</hi> 54. He may be as ſure of it, as if he had it already, or he hath it begun in him in a way and tendency to perfection; grace is glory in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, glory grace conſummate: <hi>We are changed from glory to glory;</hi> 2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>vlt.</hi> This life is begun, but ends not here; it's not of the ſoul onely, but of the body alſo; therefore Chriſt adds, <hi>I will raiſe him up at the laſt day.</hi> And of this we cannot miſs, for he prefixeth a double aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeveration, to ſtrengthen. our Faith; <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay unto you, He that believeth on me, hath everlaſting life v,</hi> 47. and tells us it was his buſineſs to accompliſh his Fathers will; <hi>I came down from Heaven, not to do mine own will, but the will of him that ſent me, v.</hi> 38.</p>
            <p>Of this alſo <hi>Peter</hi> teſtifies, <hi>When the chief Shepherd ſhall appear, ye ſhall receive a Crown of Glory that fadeth not away</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">1 Pet. 5. 4.</note>. If we receive it while we live, what becoms of it when we dy and ſhall be no more? If my ſoul muſt ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate another body, another takes my Crown, or it periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, however (as to me) it fadeth; but the Text ſets ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day when this Crown ſhall be received, and we firſt wear it; when the <hi>great Shepherd ſhall appear:</hi> This appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rition is not Spiritual to the ſoul, onely in believing; ſo he had already appeared in thoſe to whom he here writes <hi>Chap,</hi> 1. 2, 3. But this, when the Crown ſhall be put on, is to come; hear what the great Shepherd himſelf ſpeaks, as
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117882:14"/>
to the time, manner, and end of his appearing; <hi>When the Son of man ſhall come in his glory, and all the holy Angels with him, then ſhall he ſit upon the Throne of his glory, Mat. 25. 31. And before him ſhall be gathered all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and he ſhall ſeparate them one from another, as the Shepherd divideth the Sheep from the Goats. v.</hi> 32. But that is not till the end of the world, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13, 30, 37, 38, 39, 40. To the ſame effect is that of <hi>Peter, Epiſt. 1. Chap, 1. v. 3, 4, 5. Who hath begotten us again unto a lively hope, by the Reſurrection of Jeſus Christ from the dead. To an inheritance incorruptible, undefiled, and that fadeth not away, reſerved in Heaven for us. Who are kept by the Power of God through Faith unto ſalvation, ready to be revealed in the laſt time.</hi> This inheritance and ſalvation we have not in this life, for we hope for it; it is reſerved in Heaven for us, and we are kept for it, and it ſhall not be revealed till in the laſt time; and <hi>He that overcometh, ſhall inherit all things, Rev.</hi> 21. 7. Beſides, it is <hi>incorruptible and fadeth not away,</hi> which cannot ſtand with any ſtate of the Saints in this life.</p>
            <p>Nor is this only fairly concluded from, but plainly aſſerted in Scripture to be after death; whereas Hypocrites and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers have no hope in death, <hi>Iob</hi> 27. 8. the faithful have; <hi>I would not have you ignorant brethren, concerning them that are aſleep, that ye ſorrow not as others which have no hope, 1 Theſ.</hi> 4. 13. This hope is in death, as appears by the Apoſtles ſcope to comfort the Saints, and raiſe up their ſpirits, which are apt to be ſadded, and deject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with the diſeaſe of their beloved friends; and from <hi>v. 14. If we believe that Jeſus dyed and roſe again, even ſo, them alſo which ſleep in Jeſus will God bring with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For this cauſe did <hi>Paul</hi> deſire to be diſſolved; <hi>Having a deſire to depart, and to be with Christ, which is farre better</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Phil. 1. 23.</note>. He ſpeaks of dying, and that bodily, not ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally; as a way to a life and ſtate farr better then the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent:
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117882:15"/>
ſent: Nor was it <hi>Paul</hi>'s deſire onely, <hi>We that are in this Tabernacle groan, being burthened, not for that we would be unclothed, but clothed upon, that mortality might be ſwallowed up of life, 2 Cor.</hi> 5. 4. When he ſaith, not that we would be unclothed, but clothed upon; that Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality might be ſwallowed up of Life: He plainly declares this ſtate not to be while we are Mortal, and that when this Mortality ſhall be ſwallowed up of Life, a Chriſtian ſhall not onely be unclothed, and ſtript of his burthenſome, vile, and filthy garments; but be arayed afreſh with thoſe that are light, pure, and precious.</p>
            <p>What <hi>Chriſt, Paul,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> avouch, doth <hi>John</hi> from the ſame Spirit teſtifie; <hi>Rev. 14. 13. And I heard a voyce from Heaven ſaying unto me, write, Bleſſed are the dead which dy in the Lord, from henceforth; yea ſaith the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that they may reſt from their labours, and their works do follow them.</hi> Spiritually we cannot underſtand this, without manifeſt injury and violence to the Text; a man may Spiritually dy, and yet not preſently reſt from his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, as the words import; or if it be ſuppoſed the reſt promiſed may follow the death ſpecified at a diſtance, namely ſomtime after, when a man naturally dies; how is this the peculiar priviledge of thoſe that dy in the Lord? For all ſhall ſo reſt, (though they never be partakers of this Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual death in Chriſt, if there be no reſurrection of the dead body; and how do their works follow them? then how are they then bleſſed that ſhall be no more, or at leaſt not what they were before; whoſe ſouls being fired out of their old habitation, take to themſelves other dwelling places, and ſo return again to their former labours? If it be affirmed they may be happy in Heaven, though their bodies riſe not, <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſhall anſwer for me; <hi>Quomodo foelices ſi ex parte perituri?</hi> how can they be happy, who in part are pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed? Happineſs is a ſtate of perfection, but the ſoul ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from the body is incompleat and imperfect; and therefore cannot be happy, till both it and the body be
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117882:15"/>
united, to make one perfect man: Again I reply, there is no happineſs, glory, or good thing promiſed to ſoul or bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but in Chriſt raiſed from the dead; grant the body is not raiſed, you muſt yeild alſo Chriſt is not raiſed; and ſo doing you raze the very foundation of all our felicity, the houſe of our hope in all particulars thereof, muſt fall to the ground; therefore, <hi>If there be no Refurrection of the dead, and our hope onely in this life, we are of all men moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable:</hi> Which is <hi>Pauls</hi> ſecond ground in this Chapter, whereof conceiving our ſelves to have ſpoken ſufficiently, we proceed to a third.</p>
            <p>The Univerſality, Perfection, Integrity, duration of the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 8.</note> Kingdom of Chriſt, and his victory over his and our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, <hi>then cometh the end when he ſhall have delivered</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 24.</note> 
               <hi>up the Kingdom to God, even the Father; when he ſhall have put down all Rule, and all Authority and Power; v. 24. For he muſt reign till he hath put all enemies under his feet. v. 25. The laſt enemy that ſhall be deſtroyed is death. v.</hi> 26. He ſhall not deliver up his Kingdom, until he hath aboliſhed all his enemies; as Satan ſoliciting to ſin; ſin proceeding from the will of man, and death the wages of ſin. The firſt was conquered once on the Croſs, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond daily by his Spirit, the third by his appearing in the fleſh at the laſt day; although death be overcome that it cannot hurt Believers, yet is it not perfectly aboliſhed, nor they reſtored to a perfect life, until the Reſurrection of the body.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pauls</hi> next Argument is, the Teſtimony, Judgement, or <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 9.</note> Confeſſion of thoſe who were Baptized <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in our tranſlation thus: <hi>Elſe what ſhall they do which are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized for the dead; if the dead riſe not at all, why are they then baptized for the dead? v.</hi> 29.</p>
            <p>Letting paſs other expoſitions of theſe words two eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally are moſt famous and conſiderable: The firſt, that <hi>Paul</hi> alludes to a cuſtome among the <hi>Catecumeni</hi> or Novices in the Faith; who in danger of death deſired and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117882:16"/>
Baptiſm, that thereby they might both evidence, and ſtrengthen their Faith in the Reſurrection; of this practiſe <hi>Epiphanius</hi> makes mention <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Et hac de cauſa traditio, quae ad nos de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venit, eundem Sanctum Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolum dixiſſe aiunt, ſi omnino mortui non Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurgunt, cur &amp; Baptizantur, pro ipſis? cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terum alij recte hoc dictum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretantes dicuat quod morti vicini, ſi fueriut in Pietatis doctrina inſtructi ob hanc ſpem ante obitum lavacro digni fiunt; oſtendentes quod qui mortuus eſt, etiam reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get, &amp; ob id indiget remiſſione pectatorum per lavacrum.</hi> Epiph. <hi>l.</hi> 1. Tom. 2. <hi>h.</hi> 28. l <hi>Voſſij Theſ. Theol. de Reſur. carnis. th. 18. &amp; Piſcator: Anal. &amp; Schol. in</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 29.</note>. This ſuppoſed, the Apoſtle thus argues; <hi>Elſe, what ſhall they do who are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized for dead, if the dead riſe not at all why are they then baptized for dead.</hi> A ſecond ſenſe is given of this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and much contended for by learned and judicious men; the practiſs of ſome among them that were baptized over the graves and dead bodies of the Martyrs and other Saints, in teſtimony of their dying to ſin, and aſſured ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of their own, and their Reſurrection over whom they were Baptizedl.</p>
            <p>Another Argument is drawn from the Teſtimony, that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 10.</note> is, the judgement and faith of the Confeſſors, who adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and lay down their lives for Chriſt and the Goſpel; <hi>Why ſtand we in jeopardy every hour? v.</hi> 30. We give our backs to the ſmiters, and our cheeks to them that pluck off the hair; we hide not our face from ſhame and ſpetting, we count not our lives dear unto us, but continually carry them in our hands as ready to lay them down for the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; <hi>always bearing about in the body, the dying of the Lord Jeſus. And are alwayes delivered unto death for Jeſus ſake</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 13. 11.</note>. <hi>We are killed all the day long, and accounted as ſheep for the ſlaughter</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 8. 36.</note>. Some of the Saints have had <hi>tryal of cruel mockings, and ſcourgings: yea moreover, of bonds and impriſonment, They were ſlaned, they were ſawn aſunder, they were tempted, were ſlain with the ſword: they wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred about in ſheep-skins, and goat-skins, being deſtitute, affiicted, tormented. Of whom the world was not worthy, they wandred in deſerts, and in mountains, and in dens and caves of the earth</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">Heb. 11. 36. 37. 38.</note>. Others <hi>were tortured, not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117882:16"/>
deliverance;</hi> what think you moved them hereto? doubtleſs the hope of glory laid up for them in another world; it was <hi>that they might obtain a better Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>restion</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">verſe 35.</note>.</p>
            <p>Certainly theſe men were beſide themſelves, too much inconſiderate zeal had made them mad, thus to expoſe their perſons to the rage of unreaſonable men; and hereby prepare, treaſure up, and ſharpen inſtruments of death for their own tormenting; life, liberty, and eaſe are ſo ſweet, death, bonds, and pain ſo bitter, they muſt play the madmen to ſome purpoſe in the preſence of the world, to exchange the one for the other, without hope of recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence in the life to come: But we know light, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and excellent wiſdom is found in them; Who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the ſons of men, of ſo wiſe and underſtanding hearts? To whom is given the ſpirit of wiſdom and revelation in the knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt; they ſaw with other eyes then thoſe bruits, who think they ſhall dy like beaſts, and do expect no other portion then what they have in the fleſh; ſure the Spirit of the holy God made them quick of underſtanding in his fear, by whom it was given them, not onely to believe, but to ſuffer for his ſake. And certainly, <hi>God is not unrighteous, to forget their work and labour of love which they have ſhewed toward his Name</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Heb. 6. 10.</note>, but will do unto them according to the kindneſs they have done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him; with this <hi>Paul</hi> comforts the <hi>Theſſalonians, It is a manifeſt token of the righteous judgement of God, that ye may be accounted worthy of the Kingdom of God, for which ye alſo ſuffer: Seeing it is a righteous thing with God to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſe tribulation to them that trouble you: And to you who are troubled, reſt with us, when the Lord Jeſus ſhall be revealed from Heaven, with his mighty Angels</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">2 Theſ. 1. 5.</note>. This recompenſe ſhall be, when the Lord ſhall be revealed; not in this life to the Soul, ſo he was revealed to the <hi>Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> before; but after death, when he ſhall come from Heaven, and attended with the Angels of his might; ſo he
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117882:17"/>
comes not in this preſent life to any that after dy, only to thoſe that ſhall live, till the great day of the Lord; and this was the Apoſtles encouragement and conſolation in their afflictions: <hi>Our light affliction which is but for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, worketh for us a far more exceeding and eternal weight of glory;</hi> 2 Cor. 4. 17. <hi>While we look not at the things which are ſeen, but at the things which are not ſeen: for the things which are ſeen, are Temporal, but the things which are not ſeen are Eternal. v.</hi> 18</p>
            <p>And what <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of the Saints in general, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts of himſelf in particular; <hi>I proteſt by your rejoycing which I have in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, I dy daily. v. 31. If after the manner of men I have fought with beaſts at Epheſus, what advantageth it me if the dead riſe not?</hi> His hazards and ſufferings were not once or twice but daily; and thoſe not ordinary, but grievous; his life was little better then a continual dying; he fought with beaſts at <hi>Epheſus;</hi> unreaſonable, ſavage, cruel men, rather beaſts then men; which ſome underſtand of that uproar raiſed by <hi>Demetrius</hi> the Silver-ſmith, who made Shrines for <hi>Diana, Acts</hi> 19. 23, 24. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others take the words properly, and that not without reaſon: It was uſual in the Roman Empire, to condemn Malefactors to fierce and cruel beaſts, that contending with with them, they might delight the beholders; and being overcome by them, ſuffer for their deeds: This was the lot of <hi>Ignatius</hi> and other holy Martyrs, through the malice, and for the pleaſure of their enraged perſecutors; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no wonder that <hi>Paul</hi> makes mention of ſighting with beaſts at <hi>Epheſus;</hi> What though <hi>Luke</hi> paſs it by? are there not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> memorable things by him omitted, which <hi>Paul</hi> reports of himſelf? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 25. Thus <hi>Ambroſe, Theo-doret,</hi> and others underſtand <hi>Paul;</hi> and <hi>Nicephorus</hi> hath a large narration hereof <note n="s" place="margin">Niceph Hiſt. l. 11. c. 25.</note>; ſome things in him perhaps may be fabulous, but that all ſhould be ſo, is more eaſie to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm then prove; however it be, whether by men or beaſts,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117882:17"/>
               <hi>Paul</hi>'s dangers and preſſures in <hi>Aſia</hi> (by his own confeſſion) were very great, even above his ſtrength, inſomuch that he deſpaired of life, and had the ſentence of death in himſelf; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 8, 9. Did he undergo theſe things after the manner of men? That is, according to humane reaſon and prudence, or as ſome men are wont to do, for glory and honour in the world; or as others, for the good of their Countrey? Theſe inducements could have no place in <hi>Paul,</hi> or the reſt of the Martyrs; but the expectation of a glorious Reſurrection. For it no way beſeems a wiſe man to lay himſelf open unto ſo many and grievous calamities, for a falſe and feigned thing that hath no other being then in the brains of ſome fooliſh, fantaſtical, or deceitful men; and ſuch muſt the Goſpel be, if there be no Reſurrection of the dead.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtles laſt Argument is drawn from another ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 11.</note> conſequent of the contrary doctrine; If there be no Reſurrection of the dead, then <hi>let us eat and drink, for to morrow we dy:</hi> v. 32. <hi>Lude, Bibas, Comedas, poſt mortem nulla voluptas,</hi> was a familiar proverb among the <hi>Epicures.</hi> This is it the Apoſtle out of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 22. alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth here; and in other language he ſeems to ſpeak thus, If there be no Reſurrection of the dead, wherein rewards are given to the juſt, and puniſhments to the unjuſt, but that after death the ſame ſtate and condition is common to all without difference or diſtinction; certainly ſenſual delights and pleaſures of this life, are not ſo baſe and inconſiderable as the Goſpel affirms them to be, but ſomthing more of worth and value is found in them to raiſe the rate and eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of them in the minds of men, nor is there cauſe why they ſhould not be moſt vigorouſly proſecuted, and highly accounted of by all ſorts of men in the world, who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be judged very injurious to themſelves, who cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly ſtraiten themſelves in the uſe of their liberty, and abridge themſelves of any ways, means, and methods of making proviſion for, or ſacrificing to their own luſts and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:117882:18"/>
deſires; and thoſe of all men may be thought moſt wiſe, provident, and vertuous, who are ſo far indulgent to their humors and deſires, as to make no ſcruple of adventuring on any courſe that hath a tendency to their ſenſual ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and conſequently thoſe who by the Spirit of God are declared the only wiſe ones upon earth, are indeed and truth the grand fools and mad-men of the world, who without cauſe do lay ſo many ſtumbling blocks in the way of their preſent peace, eaſe, and felicity: But we know the truth of the Goſpel hath branded this Doctrine in the Fore-head, for beaſtly and damnable Falſhood and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery.</p>
            <p>Thus far out of <hi>Paul</hi> have we proved the Reſurrection <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 12.</note> of the Dead. God's juſtice requires it that every man in body as well as ſoul may receive according to his works; in this life <hi>all things come alike to all, there is one event to the righteous and to the wicked, to the good, and to the clean, and to the unclean; to him that ſacrificeth, and to him that ſacrificeth not; as is the good, ſo is the ſinner; and he that ſweareth, as he that feareth an oath; Eccleſ.</hi> 9. 2. therefore it is neceſſary there ſhould be a judgement, wherein the juſt may be viſibly and openly honoured, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted, and rewarded; the unjuſt, ſhamed, condemned, and puniſhed. Therefore ſaith <hi>Paul, We muſt all appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Judgement ſeat of Chriſt, that every one may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the things done in his body, according to that he hath done, whether it be good or bad;</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 10. and this is <hi>a righteous thing with God;</hi> 2 Theſ. 1. 6. which the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience it ſelf bears witneſs to, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 15. and for execution hereof, Chriſt is appointed Judge of quick and dead, and <note place="margin">Acts 10. 42. 2 Tim. 4. 1. 1 Pet. 4. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Acts 17. 31. He hath appointed a day, in the which he judge the World in righteouſneſs, by that man whom he will hath ordained; whereof he hath given aſſurance unto all men, in that he hath raiſed him from the dead:</hi> And this cannot be done without raiſing the dead; Therefore the twenty four Elders <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. 18. make the time of raiſing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117882:18"/>
the dead, judging and rewarding men according to their works, to be all one.</p>
            <p>And as the Juſtice, ſo the Wiſdom of God is herein <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 13.</note> engaged; It is not the part of a wiſe man to be fruſtrated and diſappointed of the end of his Workmanſhip. God hath made man after his own Image, for the manifeſtation of his Glory, and communication of his Goodneſs, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Righteouſneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that by this means he might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually ſerve and glorifie him, and be for ever made happy by him. This is not in this preſent life, therefore in an other.</p>
            <p>His Truth alſo is concerned in it, its the promiſe made <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 14.</note> unto the Fathers, <hi>Acts</hi> 26. 6, 7, 8.</p>
            <p>Beſides, Chriſt is Lord both of quick and dead, <hi>Rom.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 15.</note> 14. 9. the body ſure comes under his government, and belongs to his Dominion; And will this Prince ſuffer theſe for ever to be loſt in the grave?</p>
            <p>Alſo the names given unto death will afford us ſomwhat <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 16.</note> for our ſatisfaction in this point; It's called <hi>a Sleep,</hi> and this imports an awakening; a <hi>lying down,</hi> which preſuppoſeth a riſing up again, <hi>Job</hi> 14. 12. a <hi>Change;</hi> and therefore it is not the utter annihilation or periſhing of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. <note place="margin">Iob 14. 14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And as for the Saints, ſuch is their Relation to God <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 17.</note> and Chriſt in Covenant; they are his Workmanſhip, Spouſe, Building, Body, Temples, Friends; and can we in reaſon imagine they ſhall be ſo forgotten of him as to remain for ever in the duſt? Theſe Relations engage him to raiſe them up again; and the ſame Spirit that raiſed Chriſt, dwels in them, and becomes an aſſurance of their Reſurrection; <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 11. Therefore ſaith <hi>Job,</hi> ſpeaking of the Reſurrection, <hi>Chap. 14. 15. Thou ſhalt call, and I will anſwer thee: Thou wilt have a deſire to the work of thine hands;</hi> and God ſaith <hi>Iſe. 26. 19. Thy dead men ſhall live, my dead body ſhall they ariſe;</hi> ſo ſome read the words, they are his body though dead, dead in the grave, but
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117882:19"/>
alive to him in Covenant: Upon this very ground the p poſtle expects a Reſurrection, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 13, 14. <hi>The Body is for the Lord, and the Lord for the Body;</hi> What then? <hi>And God hath both raiſed up the Lord, and will alſo raiſe up us by his own Power.</hi> They are given unto Chriſt, and ſhall not be loſt, but raiſed up by him, <hi>John</hi> 6. 39. This is his Fathers Will; and Chriſt is ſo obedient a Son, he can omit nothing, but readily ſulſus all his pleaſure. And ſo ſure are the Saints of being raiſed up, that they are ſaid to be raiſed up already in Chriſt; <hi>and hath raiſed us up together,</hi> Eph. 2. 6. this <hi>Henoch</hi>'s tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 5. <hi>Eliah</hi>'s taking up into heaven, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 2. 11. <hi>Jonah</hi>'s delivery from the Whales belly, <hi>Jonah,</hi> 2. 10. the riſing of particular men before, with, and after Chriſt; and both the Sacraments confirm, and the Spirit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly ſeals; this the Patriarcks believed, why elſe do they <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 13.</note> confeſs themſelves ſtrangers and Pilgrims?</p>
            <p>I hope by this time you are ſo fully ſatisfied in this point, that nothing more is neceſſary to be added for your eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment, who are not engaged to your own wills, or gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven up to a ſpirit of ſlumber, but are willing to ſubmit to the evidence of Scripture, and to have your Judgements rectified, and opinions tryed by that ſacred rule; what hath been ſpoken doth ſufficiently demonſtrate the infallibility of our Poſition. Yet that the madneſs of gainſayers may be more manifeſt, and their mouths altogether ſtopped, we ſhall ſubjoyn the teſtimony and conſent of Chriſtians, Jews, Mahumetans, and Heathens, acknowledging for ſubſtance what hath been by us aſſerted.</p>
            <p>That this was the Faith of all the Orthodox Church ſince Chriſt's time, is no difficult undertaking; thoſe who are acquainted in any meaſure with the ancient records, and modern Writings of thoſe who have either as Hiſtorians reported the ſtate of the Church, or as Champions main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained her cauſe, cannot be ignorant of this thing; that in all Ages ſince Chriſt it hath been a received and unqueſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:117882:19"/>
principle among thoſe who profeſſed themſelves Chriſtians, except ſome few, whoſe abominable and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous doctrines, and beaſtly practiſes, have juſtly brand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them for bruitiſh Heretiques. In teſtimony hereof, the Decrees and Creeds of Councels, Symboles and Apologies of particular men, the Churches Champions in ſeveral Ages; Solemnities and Ceremonies at the Funerals of the dead might be produced; but we paſs theſe by, as of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in this matter.</p>
            <p>That it was the belief of the Jews, both ancient and modern, you may ſce in <hi>Galatinus de Arcanis Catholicae</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>lib.</hi> 12. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Veritatis<hi rend="sup">t</hi>,</hi> and <hi>Menaſſeh Ben Iſrael</hi> his book <hi>de Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectione Mortuorum;</hi> the Phariſees believed a Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Acts</hi> 23. 8. In the corrupt times before Chriſt, they took an Oath of the high Prieſt, when he entred into the Holieſt of all, leſt he ſhould incline to the Sadduces <note n="u" place="margin">Cunaeus de Republ Jud.</note>, the form whereof was this; <hi>We adjure thee by him who cauſed his Name to dwell in this Houſe, that thou change not any thing of that we ſhall ſay to thee.</hi> Many corruptions and ſuperſtitions indeed were mingled with it; it is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for our purpoſe they believed the main. In the times of corruption and apoſtacie they deſired to be buried in their clothes, as <hi>Monaſſeh Ben Iſracl</hi> teſtifies in the Treatiſe aforeſaid; and he among others, inſtanceth in <hi>R. Irmihah,</hi> he ſaid, Clothe me in a pure and white garment, put on my Stockings, and my Shooes, and give me my ſtaff in my hand, that when God calls, I may be ready and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared. It is the thirteenth Article of their Creed, compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by <hi>R. Moſes Ben Maimon,</hi> who dyed <hi>Anno Mundi</hi> 496 <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Buxtorf Synagog. Jud. c.</hi> 1.</note> after the Jews uſual acount and <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1104. Hence I ſuppoſe they had ſo many Solemnities about the Dead, Funeral Rites and Cuſtoms, Waſhing, Embalming <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Weems Jud. Law. l.</hi> 1 <hi>c.</hi> 44. Ezek. 24. 17.</note>, Laying the Body in a Bed of Spices, and burning ſweet Odours over it *, Feaſts <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Druſius in Eccleſiaſticum, c.</hi> 30. <hi>v</hi> 25.</note> ſetting Meat upon the Graves of the Dead *; the Burial ended, they comforted the Living after this manner; <hi>Sit Conſolatio tua in Coelis;</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:117882:20"/>
repeated that of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 25. 8. <hi>He will ſwallow up death in victory, and the Lord will wipe away tears from off all faces:</hi> and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72. 16. <hi>They of the City ſhall flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh like graſs of the earth:</hi> They writ upon the Tombs <hi>Sit Anima ejus in faſciculo vitae, cum caeteris justis, Amen, Amen, Selah;</hi> and called the Church-yard <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>The Houſe of the Living,</hi> becauſe there they are living to the Lord <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Weeins Jud. Law, l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 44.</note>: and <hi>Abraham</hi> confeſſeth himſelf a ſtranger in the land of Canaan, <hi>Gen.</hi> 23. 4. declaring thereby, <hi>he ſought another and a better Countrey, where God had prepared for him a City;</hi> Heb. 11. 13, 14, 16. And having ſojourned ſixty yeers in theſe lands, he never purchaſed foot of Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance <hi>Acts</hi> 7. 5. till now for his dead, nor for any, though many belike dyed in his houſe, but for <hi>Sarah;</hi> as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer teſtified his faith, abiding there as in a ſtrange Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 9. So this purchaſe of a grave ſheweth the like for a general Reſurrection of the dead <note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ainſworth</hi> on Gen. 23. 4.</note>; what the faith of <hi>Job, Moſes, David,</hi> and other Patriarks was we have ſhewed before in proof of the point.</p>
            <p>And this alſo doth <hi>Mahomet</hi> and his Worſhippers ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, and therefore uſe great Ceremonies about the dead, praying for them, and ſaying, God can eaſily raiſe men up again, who firſt created them of nothing: and in hope hereof they are encouraged to do many good works, and couragiouſly hazard, and cheerfully loſe their lives in defence of their Religion.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, this alſo is aſſented unto by Heathers; we ſhall name ſome of many; <hi>Zoroaſtres</hi> held all ſhould return to life <note n="a" place="margin">Lod. Vives ex Theopomp.</note>, <hi>Democritus</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Plin. Hiſt. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 55.</note>, <hi>Plato</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſt certe o Coebes maxime omnium ut mihi videtur, ex mortuis revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſcentes homines fiunt; mortuorum ſuperſunt animae, atque bonis melius eſt malis vero peius,</hi> in Phoedone.</note>, <hi>Chryſippus</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lactantius Inſtit. l.</hi> 7. c. 23.</note>, <hi>Seneca</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deſinunt iſta, non pereunt, etiam mors quam pertimeſcimus ac recuſamus intermittit vitam non eripit, veniet iterum qui nos in luce reponet dies, aequo animo debet rediturus exire.</hi> Epiſt. 36. <hi>ad</hi> Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilium.</note>, <hi>Valerius
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:117882:20"/>
Flaccus</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Patet olli Janua Lethi: At<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> iterum remeare licet: Comes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Additur &amp; pariter terros at a; square <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</note>, <hi>Virgilius</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">O Pater anne aliquas ad coe um hinc ire putandum eſt Sublimes animas, iterum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad tarda reverti Corpora? quae lucis miſeris tam dira Cupido?</note>, <hi>Claudianus</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Quos ubi per varios annos per mille figuras Egit Lethaeo purgatos flumine tandem Rurſus ad humanae revocant primordia formae.</note>, <hi>Phocylides</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>, were of the like perſwaſion, and many paſſages there are in the <hi>Sybils</hi> to this purpoſe <note n="k" place="margin">Lactant. Inſtit. l. 7. c. 24.</note>.</p>
            <p>Where the Heathens lighted their candle, we will not now enquire, being little to our purpoſe; it ſufficeth they had ſo much light in their great darkneſs, to make a diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of this hidden Myſterie. <hi>Mahomet</hi> doubtleſs had it from the Scriptures; as alſo the Jews, <hi>for unto them were committed the Oracles of God.</hi> Thus have we the conſent of Adverſaries, and thoſe very ancient (ſome of them) to confirm our Faith in this Article. This I urge not as a ground of our Belief, but as an evidence of the Antiquity of this Doctrine, and the entertainment it hath had, and now hath with the enemies of our Religion; that it may not be objected to us as a novel opinion, and in the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of wiſe and rational men, impoſſible of improbable.</p>
            <p>Having proved this point, we now addreſs our ſelves to a further explication of it; and firſt of the ſubject or matter thereof: As all ſhall riſe, ſo in the very ſame nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical body that dyes <note n="l" place="margin">Aquileienſis Eccleſia in ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolo dicebat credo Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionem carnis hutus. Voſſij Theſ. Theol. de Reſur. carnis.</note>; the ſame for ſubſtance, figure, form, members, lincaments: To prevent miſtakes herein, we muſt ſo conceive this Identity of the body which is raiſed, with that which dies; hat it doth not import the raiſing of all the ſame matter, and reſtoring to the very ſame condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:117882:21"/>
it had before the ſame numerical body in divers ages and times, admits of great variety; it is otherwiſe in child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, then youth; middle age, then old age; otherwiſe in health then ſickneſs; and when there is an integrity of all members, then when the ſame is maimed; nor doth all the ſame matter continue from firſt to laſt, from a mans birth to his death; but ſome part is by hunger and other wayes waſted, and ſupply made by nutrition; no, nor is there the ſame quantity in reſpect of extention of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but ſometimes augmentation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> other ſome diminution; not the ſame ſtature in Infancy as afterward; yea, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion is mutable, the external feature, and internal tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per changed, and yet we hold the body to be the ſame; becauſe there is remaining of the Original matter to the end of a mans days; notwithſtanding the flux and reflux of the matter in part; the ſame humane ſhape and feature, ſufficiently to diſtinguiſh him from other creatures; and when any part is exhauſted, there is a preſent ſupply, ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto the former: So that the Identity of our bodies at the Reſurrection, with theſe we now have, doth not neceſſarily enforce a reſtitution of all that matter of which our bodies here have been conſtituted; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> nor the ſame ſtate and condition in all reſpects, but ſo farr as is proper and peculiar to us, numerically to diſtinguiſh us from other men. That thus the ſame body ſhall riſe, is evident; for otherwiſe it were not a Reſurrection, but transformation, or chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from one to another, or a Creation and production of new ones not a raiſing of the old: Beſides Immortality in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptibility, power glory, ſpirituality, are promiſed to this very body; <hi>He that raiſed up Chriſt from the dead, ſhall quicken your mortal body,</hi> Rom. 8. 11. And <hi>this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible muſt put on incorruption, and this mortal muſt put on immortality,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 53 <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>In duere in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptionem, quantitativam &amp; eandem nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero eſſentiam, digito<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrans, magis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim expreſſe non poterat lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui niſi cutem ſuam manibus te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eret</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>. <hi>All that are in the graves ſhall hear his voice, and ſhall come forth, Joh.</hi> 5. 28, 29. And again, the ſame body that overcoms, ſhall wear the Crown; the ſame that ſuffers, ſhall reign with
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:117882:21"/>
Chriſt; the ſame that ſins, ſhall be puniſhed; and not others for them: <hi>Every one ſhall receive the things done in his body, according to that he hath done,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 10. And thoſe that ſhall be found alive when Chriſt comes, ſhall be changed onely, not have other bodies given them; and its not likely they ſhall have this preheminence above the dead.</p>
            <p>That of <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 21. affords ſeveral Arguments for proof hereof. He ſhall change, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> He ſhall change the faſhion of our bodies: not the ſubſtance, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 31.</note> formes, members, lineaments: The faſhion of the world paſſeth away, not the ſubſtance, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the figure or faſhion of the world: Again, he ſhall change <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> our vile body; it is in reſpect of its vile and miſerable condition by reaſon of ſin; it notes the ſtate of our body now, and what they ſhall be; our body is the ſame as before the fall, for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but not for condition; its an humbled and vile body now, but thus it ſhall not remain. And it ſhall be made like to the glorious body of Chriſt; that was the ſame for ſubſtance, form, though not for qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and ſtate, as we proved before; and is clear from <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 19. <hi>Deſtroy this Temple, and in three days I will raiſe it up.</hi> In ſhort, thoſe reaſons which we before urged in proof of the Reſurrection, prove the raiſing of the ſame body.</p>
            <p>As for thoſe parts and members of the body, as heart, head, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are neceſſarily required to fit it for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with the rational ſoul, neither juſt nor unjuſt ſhall want them; the matter ſhall be organized and faſhioned into ſuch members; for otherwiſe they could not be men, and ſo not indeed raiſed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as for thoſe integral parts of man, which are not abſolutely neceſſary, but onely for his further perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; as fingers, toes, armes, feet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is plain that the juſt ſhall not want any one of them; it will not ſtand with
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:117882:22"/>
a ſtate of perfection to be defective in any member, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore loſt members ſhall be reſtored to the Saints in glory: And becauſe the unjuſt have offended God in all their members, making them the inſtruments of unrighteouſneſs; it is probable therefore they ſhall not riſe without any of them they formerly had<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though they wanted them at the diſſolution. As for thoſe members which they never had, why they ſhould be reſtored, I ſee no cauſe; but as the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect ſhall not be wanting in any thing that conduceth to happineſs and glory: ſo to the wicked nothing ſhall be added which may diminiſh their miſery and infamy; onely the blind are to be reſtored, that they may ſee him whom they have pierced, and behold their Judge; and the deaf, that they may hear him to their terrour.</p>
            <p>And whereas there are ſome things pertaining to the nature of man in reſpect of his preſent ſtate, and according to the common and ordinary courſe of Nature, as humours, ſeed, milk, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We ſuppoſe that both ſhall have thoſe things that are receſſary, in the number of which, we do not comprehend ſuperfluous or excrementitious humours, or thoſe which are of Nature intended for generation; as ſeed, or nutrition of another, as milk, of which there ſhall be no uſe; of thoſe things which humane nature cannot here want, as blood, I conceive this ſhall be reſtored alſo; yet to ſome this ſeems rather agreeing to a natural than a Spiritual body: And although ſome members are of no uſe in the Reſurrection, yet for as much as of the Orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical members there is a double relation, the firſt of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the form, ſo their end is the perfecting and adorning the body or of an Organ to an active Principle; ſo the end is operation, though there be no need of ſome members as to operation; yet in reſpect of ornament and perfection of the body, they are not in vain, or ſuperfluous, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in the Reſurrection; ſo that though there be no uſe, yet there ſhall be diſtinction of the Sex.</p>
            <p>As to the quantity and ſtature of the body, ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:117882:22"/>
all ſhall ariſe at the ſame ſtature to which they ſhould have come, and beyond which they ſhould not have gone, if Nature had not erred; but this we ſhall not aſſert, or undertake to determine.</p>
            <p>The bodyes of the unjuſt ſhall be made immortal and incorruptible, but paſſible: they ſhall receive their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, not for Ornament, but torment; for they muſt be tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, and ſuffer the wrath of the Almighty for ever and ever; therefore it is neceſſary they ſhould dy no more, but remain for ever without natural helps, that they may be puniſhed without intermiſſion.</p>
            <p>The Saints ſhall be raiſed to a perfect and glorious e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, they ſhall be like Chriſts glorious body, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 21. and like the Angels of God, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. 30.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In Immortality, <hi>Neither ſhall they dy any more.</hi> Luke 20. 36. <hi>This mortal muſt put on immortality.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. And <hi>we groan, that mortality might be ſwallowed up of life.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 4. And death is ſaid to be <hi>ſwallowed up in victory,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 54. So that <hi>there ſhall be no more death, Apoc.</hi> 21. 4. Death it ſelf being <hi>caſt into the lake of fire, Apoc.</hi> 20. 14. Others raiſed before Chriſt, and ſome after by the Apoſtles, dyed again; but to theſe ſhall be no dying, for ſuch was Chriſts life; Chriſt <hi>being raiſed from the dead, dyeth no more, death hath no more domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over him, Rom.</hi> 6. 9.</p>
            <p>Our life ſhall be parallel to eternity; the body before the Fall was immortal, therefore did God place in Paradiſe the Tree of Life, as a Sacrament of that immortality he ſhould have enjoyed in his innocent ſtate: The long life of <hi>Adam</hi> and the Fathers, was the Reliques of that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality man had before the Fall. And this is the ſtate of the holy Angels, their days are the days of Eternity. God is immortal by Nature; thus he only hath immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 16. The Angels and ſouls of men by Creation; <hi>Adam</hi>'s body by condition, if he brake not Covenant with his Maker, ours hereafter by ſpecial grace
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:117882:23"/>
in the Reſurrection; for the cauſe removed, the effect muſt ceaſe; ſin is taken away, therefore death alſo in due time muſt be removed; the Guilt of ſin is taken away in Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, the Reign of it in Converſion, the Acting of it in Death, the laſt Effect in the Reſurrection. <hi>Adam</hi> before the Fall was Potentially mortal, as the effect proves; he ſhould have been immortal, if he had kept the conditions of the Covenant; thoſe that are raiſed, ſhall be ſo confirmed that they cannot dy; for they ſhall not be in a capacity of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which brings death; they have not this immortality upon ſuch termes as <hi>Adam</hi> had.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In Incorruptibility, and Impaſſibility, they ſhall not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any thing that can hurt, afflict, or impair them; <hi>It is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 43. 52. 53. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſown in corruption, it is raiſed in incorruption. The dead ſhall be raiſed incorruptible: this corruptible muſt put on incorruption.</hi> Now our bodies by hunger, thirſt, diſeaſes, labcur, grief, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are waſted every day, and at laſt whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly corrupted in our diſſolution; but after the Reſurrection they ſhall continue in the ſame ſtate. The Manna which by man could not be kept one day without putrifaction, by the Divine power was preſerved in the golden Pot for many ages; <hi>Aegyptians</hi> by embalming bodies, kept them from corruption many hundred years; and why may not an immortal body be kept from corruption by an Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent God? And thus alſo ſhall the Saints be as the Angels.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In Power, <hi>It is ſown in weakneſs, it is raiſed in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 43.</note> 
               <hi>Power:</hi> Here it is weak and ſickly, then it ſhall be ſtrong, vigorous, and healthy; the ſtrength of <hi>Sampſon</hi> and other mighty men in a fallen ſtate, ſhew what <hi>Adams</hi> was by Creation, and what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhall be in the Reſurrection; for this is a reſtauration of what we loſt, and of further per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. The powerfulneſs of the body in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection comprehends,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Activeneſs</hi> in the execution of all thoſe actions which are ſuitable to it; our bodies now are impotent, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:117882:23"/>
ſo indiſpoſed to perform all thoſe actions that belong to them, and unſerviceable to the ſoul; yet when this great change ſhall come, they ſhall be made able to act perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; they ſhall be obſervant of, and ſubſervient to the ſouls deſires; and whereas now their gravity doth hinder their motion upward, they ſhall then like Eagles, mount up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Ayr, and convey themſelves whither they pleaſe, for they ſhall be filled with the Spirit: An Egg cannot mount upward while it is without life, but when it is quickened and filled with ſpirits, it moveth, and mounteth on high. A Bird is an heavy body, yet by her wings ſhe can raiſe her ſelf from the earth, and fly ſwiftly in the Ayr. Iron may be ſo formed by Art, that it ſhall not ſink, but ſwim upon the water; and why ſhould this motion of our bodies after the Reſurrection be thought incredible? Chriſts body could move upward, for it aſcended into Heaven, and ours ſhall be like it; when he comes, <hi>we ſhall be caught up to meet the Lord in the Ayr.</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. 17.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Nimbleneſs,</hi> Strength puts Agility into bodies, makes them more quick in motion; <hi>Aſahel</hi> was ſwift as a <note place="margin">2 Sam. 2.</note> Roe: Our bodies muſt be more perfect, being conformed to Chriſt, who was ſo quick in motion, that he vaniſhed out of ſight, when he had ſhewed himſelf to his Diſciples. <note place="margin">Luke 24. 31.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Unweariedneſs,</hi> now we are ſoon tyred with action by reaſon of weakneſs, but then we ſhall be ſo ſtrong and lively, that we ſhall be unwearied in all our actions and motions.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In Glory, <hi>It is ſown in diſhonour, it is raiſed in glory:</hi> Which glory ſtands in the integrity, beauty, and <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 43.</note> ſplendor of all members; they ſhall be raiſed perfect, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no deformity, through defect of convenient members, or congruous quantity, or through acceſſion of ſome mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber or part, inconvenient or diſproportioned in ſcituation, or uncomlineſs in any kind whatſoever; the body which is now foul, filthy, without beauty, or ſplendor, ſhall be
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:117882:24"/>
made lightſome, clear, and ſhining, clothed with heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly glory and Divine light. When Chriſt was transfigured on mount <hi>Tabor, his Face did ſhine as the Sun, and his raiment was white as the light. Mat.</hi> 17. 2. It may well be ſuppoſed, it hath no leſs, but rather greater beauty now, ſince hi is entred into his glory; for ſome reaſons this glory might be vailed before his Aſcenſion, but the Apoſtle is plain for his glorious ſtate now, and ours in conformity thereto: <hi>Who ſhall change our vile bodies, that it may be faſhioned like unto his glorious body, Phil.</hi> 3. 21. <hi>and we ſhall be like him.</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 2. The glory of his transfiguration was a fore runner, not of his own only, but of our glory alſo in heaven; the ſame it was for Eſſence with what he had af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, though, different in circumſtance and degrees; that onely for a ſeaſon, but this for ever; that tranſient, this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent; <note place="margin">Pſal. 45.</note> Chriſt in the fleſh was <hi>fairer then the ſons of men in his low eſtate, white and ruddy, the chief of ten thouſand: Cant.</hi> 5. And is he not beautiful, being highly exalted at the right hand of God? This beauty is made up of the integrity of his body in reſpect of the number, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and perfection of his members, and proportion in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and exceeding brightneſs, and heavenly ſplendor; and ſuch ſhall be our glory and beauty of our bodies in the world to come; now we have blemiſhes, but then we ſhall have none; yea, not onely our imperfections ſhall be done away, but a new beauty conferred on us. <hi>In all Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael there was none to be ſo much praiſed as</hi> Abſolom <hi>for his beauty. From the ſoal of his foot, even to the Crown of his head, there was no blemiſh in him:</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14. 25. Of the <hi>Nazarites</hi> 'tis ſaid, <hi>they were purer then Snow, they were whiter then Milk they were more ruddy in body then Rubies. Lam.</hi> 4. 7. <hi>Moſes</hi> face ſhone ſo, that he put on a Vail when he ſpake to the people; and of <hi>Stephen</hi> 'tis ſaid, <hi>they that ſate in the Councel, looking ſtedfaſtly on him, ſaw his face, as it had been the face of an Angel. Acts</hi> 6. 25. All that glory I conceive no glory, in compariſon of this at
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:117882:24"/>
the Reſurrection; <hi>When they that be wiſe ſhall ſhine as the brightneſs of the Firmament, and they that turn many to righteouſneſs, as the Stars for ever and ever.</hi> Dan. 12. 2. <hi>And the Righteous ſhine forth as the Sun in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Father. Mat.</hi> 13. 43. We ſhall all have the ſame glory for Eſſence, but not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> degrees; but as <hi>there is one glory of the Sun, another glory of the Moon, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther glory of the Stars, and one Star differeth from another Star in glory, ſo alſo is the Reſurrection of the dead.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 41, 42. All Stars are not of one magnitude, nor all Saints the ſame in glory; all ſhall be fair, pure, clear, beautiful, and delightful to behold, having all mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of a comly proportion, and amiable colour, and ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in glory; no deformity by defect, redundancy or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportion in any part, in reſpect of matter or colour.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Spirituality; <hi>It is ſown a natural body, it is raiſed a Spiritual body:</hi> 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 15. 44. not for ſubſtance, but qualities, conditions, and gifts of the Spirit, being by the Divine power ſuſtained and acted immediately.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whereas now it is ſupported by natural helps, Food, Phyſick, Fire, Clothing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then God ſhall be all theſe to the body; <hi>They ſhall hunger no more, neither thirſt any more, neither ſhall the Sun light on them, nor any heat,</hi> Rev. 7. 16. <hi>For the Lamb which is in the midſt of the Throne ſhall feed them, and ſhall lead them to living Fountains of water. v.</hi> 17. <hi>Moſes, Elijah,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> were preſerved forty days without food on earth, why ſhould not our bodies be preſerved thus without means for ever in heaven?</p>
            <p n="2">2. It ſhall be under the guidance, conduct and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Spirit, immediately in all its motions and actions; here the ſoul immediately caries and commands the body, but there the Spirit of God both ſoul and body where it liſteth, and acts as it pleaſeth without difficulty or wearineſs; they ſhall wholly give up themſelves to the command of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:117882:25"/>
We now proceed to the efficient cauſe of this great work; and that can be no other then God. It's a miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous work, and a new Creation; and ſo above the power of Nature to effect; and proper to God, who is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of Nature. The ancient Rabbins ſaid, There be three <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Menaſſ. Ben Iſrael, de reſur. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2. c. 1.</note> Keys in the hand of the bloſſed God, which are not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to any Legate; the <hi>Womb,</hi> the <hi>Rain,</hi> and the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the Dead;</hi> that is, He maketh the barren to Bear, cauſeth the Rain, and raiſeth the Dead. This is that Dew in <hi>Iſa. 26. 19. Thy Dew is as the dew of Herbs,</hi> or as the dew of light, the morning dow, which refreſheth, recreates graſs and the herbs, and cauſeth them to flouriſh; thy Dew, the Divine Power by which thy dead ſhall be quickned and revived, is as the Dew that falleth on the Herbs; it ſhall ſo raiſe them, as the Herbs that are decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and withered, are raiſed up by the morning Dew; and comfortable heat and influence of the Sun. <hi>God who quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the Dead,</hi> as <hi>Rom. 4. 17. Who quickneth all things,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 13. <hi>Which raiſeth the Dead,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Cor. 1. 9. it is an Act common to all the three Perſons, Father, Son, and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; The Father raiſeth up the dead, and quickneth them; <hi>John</hi> 5. 21. and the Spirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 11. The Son, <hi>John</hi> 5. 21. <hi>Even ſo the Son quickneth whom he will:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt promiſeth it, <hi>I will raiſe him up at the laſt day,</hi> John 6. 40. 44, 54. and <hi>John 11. 25. I am the Reſurrection, and the Life:</hi> How is that? Not Formally, but Cauſally; I am the Cauſe of the Reſurrection and Life that any man hath; None riſe or live but by me. This from Chriſt's mouth the Apoſtles preached and belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, knowing that <hi>he which raiſed up the Lord Jeſus, ſhall raiſe up us alſo by Jeſus;</hi> 2 Cor. 4. 14. Thus in <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem they taught the People, and preached through Jeſus the Reſurrection of the Dead:</hi> And alſo at <hi>Athens, Paul preached Jeſus, and the Reſurrection; Chap.</hi> 17. 18. And thus doth he anſwer the firſt <hi>Adam; As in Adam all dy, ſo in Chriſt ſhall all be made alive;</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 22.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:117882:25"/>
All good and bad by his Power, for he hath <hi>the Keys of Hell and Death;</hi> Apoc. 1. 18. He hath Power as God, and Commiſſion from God (as man) to raiſe the Dead: This he doth by vertue of his Office, all Judgement being committed to him as the ſon of man. Therefore Raiſing the Dead, and Judging them being raiſed, are put together, <hi>John</hi> 5. 21, 22, 27. He ſhall at the laſt day by his voice awaken all that are a ſleep in the duſt; <hi>They that are in the grave ſhall hear his voice;</hi> John 5. 28. As the natural Voice raiſeth him that ſleepeth, ſo the Voice of Chriſt raiſeth the Dead; it is likely that ſhall be a real and articulate voice, namely, ſuch a one as ſhall ſound out ſome ſuch ſentence as this, <hi>Ariſe ye dead, and come to Judgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in an eſpecial manner Chriſt is the cauſe of the Saints reſurrection, as he is their Head; Firſt, He is an effective principle of riſing to all his Members, therefore called the Beginning, the Firſt-born of the Dead, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 18. The firſt Fruits of them that ſlept, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 20. and a quickning Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 45. The power by which we are raiſed, is with Chriſt <hi>per modum redundantiae,</hi> it abounds in him, even to overflowing; there is not only a ſufficiency of power for his own riſing, but a redundancy for ours alſo: All things tending to our ſalvation are in his hands, he is entruſted with power for our good, as in other things, ſo in this, the raiſing of our bodies: He hath not life for his own perſon alone, but treaſures of life for every member; as he hath life in himſelf, ſo it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to all his members. We have it from him by way of Influence; Chriſt, God-man, raiſeth us; the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er not humane, but divine; the ſame by which his own body was raiſed; yet his Humanity concurring thus far, the Deity not raiſing us without the Will and conſent of the humanity: Yea, as man, he deſires, purpoſeth, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth the raiſing of our bodies.</p>
            <p>Secondly, He is the meritorious cauſe, he hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:117882:26"/>
life for his, and redeemed them from death by a price, taken away ſin the cauſe of death, ſatisfied divine Juſtice, and ſo procured full and compleat Redemption for them; <hi>He was delivered for our offences, and was raiſed again for our Juſtification, Rom.</hi> 4. 25. and if we be juſtified, then we ſhall alſo be glorified.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He is the exemplary cauſe; we ſhall be conformed to him in this alſo. He was raiſed, as a pattern and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to all his Members, holding forth the manner of their reſurrection in his; <hi>Who ſhall change our vile body, that it may be faſhioned like unto his glorious body,</hi> Phil. 3. 21. the Reſurrection that he ſhewed in himſelf, he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to us.</p>
            <p>The Final cauſe or end of the Reſurrection, the glory of God in the patefaction of his God-head, Truth, Mercy, Juſtice, Power, Wiſdom, and Providence; that the whole man may be judged before the Tribunal of God, and all men receive according to their works, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 10. that as ſoul and body have ſerved God, or ſinned together, ſo they may be rewarded or puniſhed together; that the Saints with Chriſt their Head, may both in ſoul and body be for ever bleſſed in heaven, and the wicked with Satan their head, be eternally tormented in hell. Although all riſe, yet is there a different end and iſſue of their reſurrection; to ſome it is a reſurrection to life and glory, who are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called the children of the reſurrection, <hi>Luke</hi> 20. 36. to others a reſurrection to death, ſhame, and condemnation, <hi>Dan. 12. 2, 3. John 5. 28, 29.</hi> therefore were the Saints buried together, and ſtrangers apart, becauſe they expected a better reſurrection.</p>
            <p>But when ſhall theſe things be?</p>
            <p>In the end of the world, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 39, 40. at the laſt day, <hi>John 6. 39, 40, 44, 54. When Chriſt ſhall deliver up his Kingdom to the Father, and put down all rule authority, and power, 1 Cor.</hi> 15. 23, 24.</p>
            <p>Now that we may leave no way unattempted which
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:117882:26"/>
may conduce to the clearing of this truth, ſilencing of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictors, and ſatisfying of the ſcrupulous, we ſhall in the next place examine and make anſwer to what is uſually pleaded againſt it; and I truſt you will in concluſion plainly perceive (the moſt ponderous Arguments and Doubts being laid in the ballance) will be found wanting, and of no weight at all, but lighter then vanity. All that can be urged is againſt to the poſſibility of the thing in reſpect of the power of that cauſe which muſt effect it, or probability and infallibility thereof in reſpect of his Will. In ſhort, it is conceived difficult to be done, and in ſome mens fancies ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver promiſed.</p>
            <p>It is ſuppoſed contrary to ſenſe or reaſon, becauſe of the <note place="margin">Objection,</note> diſſipation of our bodies, which are reſolved into Elements, and are ſo mingled with them and other bodies, that it ſeems a thing impoſſible they ſhould be drawn out and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from them.</p>
            <p>To this we reply, <hi>The things which are impoſſible with</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Solution,</note> 
               <hi>men, are poſſible with God;</hi> Luke 18. 27. <hi>Is any thing too hard for the Lord?</hi> Gen. 18. 14. The queſtion ſhould thus be reſolved, there is not any thing too hard for the Lord, that is, which doth not in it ſelf imply a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, or in him denote imperfection; we muſt not judge of the power of God by what we ſee in the creature, nor limit it to what we find in our ſelves; <hi>Canſt thou by ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing find out God? Canſt thou find out the Almighty to perfection? Job</hi> 11. 7. This then being preſuppoſed, we make not Nature, but the God of Nature the worker of this great miracle; why ſhould it ſeem either ſtrange or impoſſible? Senſe and Reaſon is but a crooked line to meaſure his power, and too ſhort to ſound his Almighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; though it may ſeem above, yet it is not contrary to Reaſon; the moſt can be ſaid, it exceeds the reach of meer ſenſe, it can with no ſenſe be affirmed repugnant to it, For God is able to raiſe the dead, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 19. It de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notes not imperfection in him to do it, nor doth it in it ſelf
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:117882:27"/>
involve any repugnancy why it cannot be done; <hi>God is able of ſtones to raiſe up children unto Abraham, Mat.</hi> 3. 8. and why not the ſame body out of the duſt and animate it by the ſame ſoul by which it was formerly enlivened. Again, where the ſame numerical principles (Matter and Form) of the thing or Perſon corrupted remain, and the ſame Agent who did firſt put them together, continues in the ſame power ſtate and condition; what can hinder why they cannot be united and reſtored again to the ſame ſtate wherein they were before ſeparation? The Agent remains, God changeth not, and his Arm is not ſhortned. And that the Form, the ſoul remains, is clear from <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. 28. and <hi>Jude</hi> 7. As for the Matter, that remains alſo. The firſt Matter is held by Phyloſophers, ingenerable and incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; <note place="margin">Ariſt. Phyſ. l. 1. ad finem.</note> and the bones and fleſh of our bodies (though reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into elements) is not annihilated, but remains ſtill, and hath a being in the world; the place whereof is not hid to God, but naked and open before him.</p>
            <p>Add hereunto the natural inclination and propenſity of the ſoul to be united to the body, it being the form there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, cannot but have a diſpoſition to be conjoyned with it, ſith it is imperfect and incompleat in a ſtate of ſeparation: though this cannot be effected by any Natural power, yet it exceeds not the power of an Infinite Agent. God being the Author and Lord of Nature, can according to his pleaſure intend, extend, contract, and change Nature, and ſo recal the dead to life <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Idoneus eſt reficere qui fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit.</hi> Tertul. <hi>Quare mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur? quare non credimus? Deus eſt qui fecit, conſidera cuthorem &amp; tolle dubitatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</hi> Auguſt.</note>; Therefore the doctrine of the Reſurrection is not of that ſort of Contradictories.</p>
            <p>Beſides, it may be more rationally concluded, and more eaſily believed, that a Subject can again receive that influx of God which once it had, then that which it never had; A Firebrand once lighted and quench'd, is more apt to be inflam'd; and why ſhould we think it a more difficult work to reunite ſoul and body, then at firſt to unite them. Rabbi <hi>Ame</hi> anſwered after this manner to a certain Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure; A King commanded his ſervant to build him a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:117882:27"/>
Tower, where there was neither water nor earth, they o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed; and built it; in proceſs of time, this Tower came to nine the King bids them go and build him a Tower: in a certain place where there was water and earth; they reply, it is above their ability to raiſe ſuch a Fabrick; the King anſwers, if you could erect a Tower in that place where there was neither water nor earth, how much more in this where they both abound <note n="q" place="margin">Menaſſeh Bea Iſrael, de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrect mortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum l. 1. c. 4. Cur gentes des qui mortuos exciteturum ſe promiſes, non credant? quaſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fieri non poſſit, cum homo inſit poteſtate in Element is, quemadmedum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ute cum creare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ſic etiam nunc cum iterum creatur. <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> Apolog.</note>.</p>
            <p>When both theſe Principles were not, he gave us a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; how much more can he unite them, when they are diſſolved? this building when it is fallen down, he can as eaſily repair, as raiſe it when it was not; It is more incredible, that when we are not in the body, of ſo ſmall a quantity of ſeed, bones, nerves, and fleſh, in ſuch a Figure as we ſee, ſhould be formed and faſhioned; and yet doth not this come to paſs every day? And how many other wonders do we ſee in Nature every day? Wonder they would be thought, were they not ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; and incredible to ſome, were they not ſeen, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported onely: Experience proves it true, and we doubt not; the Load-ſtone draws Iron, and the Needle points to the North-pole, though reaſon dictates no ſuch thing; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we apprehend it by ſenſe, and ſee it with out eyes, we think it no deluſion. Some ſay the Sea-fiſh <hi>Echinus</hi> although ſhe be taken and torn in pieces, yet if the pieces be taken and thrown into the Sea, you may perceive them come together by little and little. But that is moſt memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable which is written of the <hi>Phoenix,</hi> that which growing <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Pliny l. 11. c.</hi> 36.</note> old, comes into <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and there (not in the deſart, but open City) with Caſſia and other materials, builds her a neſt, fils it with Odours, in which ſhe dies and putrifies; of whoſe putrifi'd fleſh a Worm is generated, and this form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into a Bird <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cyril Hiere. ſol. Catech.</hi> 18.</note> or as others report, by the beams of the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:117882:28"/>
Sun her neſt is ſet on fire, and ſhe burnt to aſhes; out of which ariſes another <hi>Phoenix;</hi> of her <hi>Cyril</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Admiranda quidem avis eſt Phoenix, ſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis tamen irra tionalis, neque unquam volans per aerem pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebat deo, neque ſcit quis ſit u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigenitus dei filius; ergo ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manti quidem irrationali, &amp; non cognoſcenti factorem ſuum Reſurrectio do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur? nobis vero glorifican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus Deum, &amp; mandata ejus cuſtodientibus eadem non da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur? Catech.</hi> 18.</note>, <hi>Clemens, Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian, Ambroſe</hi> and other Fathers write, proving thence the reſurrection: of her alſo <hi>Solinus, Tacitus, Pliny</hi> and other Naturaliſts and Hiſtorians ſpeak: <hi>Dion</hi> reports that this Bird was ſeen towards the latter end of <hi>Tiberius</hi>'s Empire <note n="w" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chron. Cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> p.</hi> 203.</note>.</p>
            <p>But becauſe this may be ſuppoſed a Fable, let us take into conſideration ſome of thoſe miraculous changes which are in Scripture upon record: <hi>Moſes</hi> rod turn'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Serpent, <hi>Aarons</hi> budding, Bitter waters made ſweet, water turned into Wine, yea, and many dead raiſed; ſome in the old Teſtament of whom, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 35. Son of the widdow of <hi>Zarephath, 1 Kin.</hi> 18. And of the <hi>Shuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite, 2 Kin.</hi> 4. 32. A dead man laid by <hi>Eliſha</hi>'s body, 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 13. 21. More in the New: <hi>Jairus</hi> daughter, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9. 25. The ſon of the widdow of <hi>Naim, Luk, 7. 15. La zarus, Ioh.</hi> 11. 43, 44, and 12. 1. 9. 17. <hi>Tabitha, Ast</hi> 9. 40. <hi>Euticus, Act.</hi> 20. 9, 10, 11. Many at Chriſts Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. 52, 53.</p>
            <p>That which hath been already done, what hinders but that it may be done again? God foreſeeing the incredulity of men, hath afforded them ſo many examples that they might believe: You ſee its plainly written in the book of Scripture, and as much (though not the ſame) you may every day read in the book of nature; the viciſſitude of things declare it poſſible, <hi>Dies moritur in noctem, &amp; rurſus cum ſuo cultu univerſo orbi reviviſſit</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">l. de Reſur. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>: Do we not ſee the day to dy at night, and ariſe as it were to a new life the next morning; the Sun having with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn himſelf for a ſeaſon, appears again, as a Bridegroom coming out of his chamber; and rejoyceth as a ſtrong man to run his race; Trees, and Plants, which in Winter are dead, and withered, in Spring revive: Swallows, Worms, and Flies, by the Winter cold caſt into a dead ſleep, are by the Summers heat awakened: But theſe ceaſe not to be, only for a time ſuſpend their acting; and are raiſed, not from
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:117882:28"/>
death, but ſleep; what is this to mans Reſurrection? We have reſemblances of this alſo; how is the Silk-worm and the Bee generated? Is the Worm made lively of a dead carcaſs, a Bird formed and faſhioned with fleſh wings, Veins, Bones, Feathers, and ſeveral parts from a moyſt Egg? And may not the ſame be done to the body of man? The ſeed which is caſt into the earth dies, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward is quickned and ſprings up again; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 36. It is ſown naked, it riſes clothed; it is ſown ſingle, riſes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold: Why ſhould it not be thought as poſſible, that man dying ſhould live again <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Qui granae ſeminum mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua, &amp; putrefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta, vivificat per quae in hoe ſeculo vivas, multo magis te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſum exſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit ut vivas in aeternum:</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt.</note>?</p>
            <p>Nor can the reſolution of his body into Elements, or their ſeparation hinder: The Goldſmith by his Art can ſunder divers Mettals mingled together, the Alchymiſt out of one draw another; ſhall impotent man do ſuch things, and the Omnipotent not be able to ſeparate thoſe Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments into which thy body is changed, from thoſe with which it is mixed? what ever confuſion or mixture there be in the world, in reſpect of us, there is none to God; all things are obvious to him, and diſtinguiſhed by his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: Why ſhould the matter of our bodyes turned to Ayre, Water, Earth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> lie hid to him, to whom the whole world is far leſs then a little Cloſet or narrow Cheſt to the wiſeſt man? the World is his Treaſury, Fire, Ayre, Earth, and Water ſo many rooms where the matter of our bodys is laid up; he knows right well how each part is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of, where it lies, and can bring it forth at his pleaſure he can call out, can bring forth what over hath been devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by Beaſts, eaten by men, deſtroyed by fiſhes, conſumed by fire, exhaled into ayre, converted into earth, reſolved into water, and how ever afterward diſperſed into this Univerſe: Neither is there any Den, Covert, Corner, Hole, or ſecret place, hidden from the knowledge, or beyond the Power of the Creator.</p>
            <p>Though this matter paſs into a thouſand bodies, one after another, as if a man be devoured by Beaſts, they ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:117882:29"/>
by Men, thoſe Men ſwallowed by Fiſhes, thoſe Fiſhes again by Men; and theſe reſolved into Ayre and other E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements; the matter of the firſt man is not in the dark, but in the light to him, how many changes ſoever there be, he can reſtore to him his own; the fleſh of the dead which is made the fleſh of another living man, is not ſo made his fleſh, but that it may be reſtored unto the firſt owner to repair his body, in whom it firſt began to be humane fleſh: But how ſhall the man eater be repaired? That in him which is exhauſted by hunger, and exhaled into ayre, or any way loſt or impaired, before his ſupply from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers fleſh, is ſo laid up in Gods Store-houſe, (though mingled with the Elemens, or in other bodies) God can find it cut and will return it unto him, that he needs not that borrowed fleſh for his ſupply; there is enough of his own in Gods keeping) to make him up a man, without being beholding to anorher for the leaſt parcel of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. We muſt not imagine, that whatſoever entreth into the body, is turned into the ſubſtanc of it; for part paſſeth away into the draught: Nor that all that is turned into the ſubſtance of the body, is permanent, and continueth with a man until the day of death, and ſo muſt riſe again and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a part of the body at the day of judgement; but eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man ſhall have ſo much of his own ſubſtance, as ſhall make his body perfect, though another mans fleſh eaten by him be no part thereof. And now I ſuppoſe, it cannot be thought impoſſible that God ſhould raiſe the dead, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he will is the main queſtion; the <hi>Libertines</hi> ſayes no: And why I pray you is not this like to be done? Here <note place="margin">Object.</note> the Devil is changed into an Angel of Light, and pleads Scripture, or rather wreſts it to maintain an Hereſie; <hi>Eccl. 3. 19. That which befalleth the ſons of men, befal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth beaſts, even one thing befalleth them; as the one dyeth, ſo dyeth the other; yea, they have all one breath, ſo that a man hath no preheminence above a beaſt:</hi> Beaſts dy, and riſe not again, and therefore no Reſurrection to be expected by the ſons of men.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:117882:29"/>
Theſe words import no more then a ſimilitude, in ſome <note place="margin">Sol.</note> things, not in all between a man and a beaſt; one thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falleth them both, that is death, and in this, a man hath no preheminence above a beaſt, to be free from death; the accord is not in all things, is evident from <hi>v. 21. Who knoweth the Spirit of man that goeth upward, and the Spirit of the beaſt that goeth downward to the earth?</hi> They both dy, but are not both alike in death; this then makes nothing againſt the Reſurrection of the body, ſith it ſpeaks not any thing of the ſtate of men and beaſts after death, but onely affirms them both to be mortal.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Cor. 15. 50. Now this I ſay Brethren, that fleſh and blood</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Object.</note> 
               <hi>cannot inherit the Kingdom of God:</hi> Therefore there can be no reſurrection of the body conſiſting of fleſh and blood.</p>
            <p>Whereas <hi>Paul</hi> affirms fleſh and blood cannot inherit <note place="margin">Sol.</note> the Kingdome of God, he means not our bodies ſimply, or according to their ſubſtance, conſiſting of fleſh and blood, as if the nature of fleſh and blood were to be aboliſhed, and not to enter into the Kingdome of God in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection; but that which before he calles a <hi>natural body, v.</hi> 44, and which is <hi>Earthy, v.</hi> 48. conformed to the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the earthly, <hi>v.</hi> 29. that is our bodies, as we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them from the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> tainted with ſin, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to infirmities; our bodies in weakneſs vileneſs, corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibility, mortality, and as they now are, before they be changed, theſe cannot inherit the Kingdome of God; this verſe is an exegeſis or explication of the former, <hi>As we have borne the Image of the Earthy, we ſhall alſo bear the Image of the Heavenly.</hi> As we have been conformable to the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> in having natural bodies, ſo we ſhal be made like the ſecond, in having Spiritual bodies: and this is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, becauſe elſe we cannot inherit the Kingdome of God; we muſt be changed, not in ſubſtance, but quality; of natural, be made Spiritual; of earthy, Heavenly; of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, Immortal; of corruptible, Incorruptible; of diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, Glorious; of weak, Powerful; of ſinful, Holy; before
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:117882:30"/>
we are capable of that Heavenly Kingdome, and Glorious ſtate of the Saints after the Reſurrection; and this is evident by what the Apoſtle adds in the cloſe of this, and in other verſes following; <hi>Neither doth corruption inherit Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption;</hi> and <hi>v. 51. We ſhall all be changed;</hi> and 52. <hi>The dead ſhall be raiſed incorruptible, and we ſhall be changed.</hi> and <hi>v. 53. This corruptible muſt put on incorruption, and this mortal, muſt put on Immortality:</hi> The old bodies ſhall remain, but clothed a new; the ſubſtance continue, but the qualities be changed; the ſame fleſh and blood, but in a better condition.</p>
            <p>If the ſouls are now free and bleſſed deniſons of Heaven, <note place="margin">Object.</note> how is it likely they ſhould deſcend again into theſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and be again captivated in them? Are not our bodies as weights, Plummets, and Shackles to the ſoul, hindring them in Divine contemplation, and Heavenly converſation?</p>
            <p>Our bodies are not naturally a burden, offence, or hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance <note place="margin">Sol.</note> to the Soul in the diſcharge of her duty, or exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of her faculties, but by accident, as they are ſinful, and ſubjected thereby to weakneſs and infirmities; all which ſhall be done away in the world to come.</p>
            <p>Our bodies are Elementary, wherein Earth and Water <note place="margin">Object.</note> are predominant, and that makes them heavy; for which cauſe they are placed where weighty and heavy things are to be ſeated; and this heavineſs of the body, muſt needs be an hindrance to the ſouls motion and action: Beſides, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is no place for ſuch bodies, there is neither lightneſs nor heavineſs, gravity, nor levity; then what ſhall our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies do in Heaven, or how ſhall they there long continue?</p>
            <p>Let not Impotent man limit the Omnipotent; God who <note place="margin">Sol.</note> made our bodies we now poſſeſs, thus qualified for our continuance in this world, can, and will make them ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the ſtate and condition of that to come; he that made the Iron to ſwim,, and ballanceth the waters in the Clouds, who to prevent vacuity, cauſeth waters to mount upward, and Iron by the influence of the Load-ſtone to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:117882:30"/>
hang in the Ayr, who gave ability to the body of Chriſt after his Reſurrection, to aſcend into the Heavens can as well change the temper of our bodies, and make them fit for any place or motion, and to continue above the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Region.</p>
            <p>From the proof and explication of this Myſtery, we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proceed <note place="margin">Vſe 1.</note> to a brief Application. What hath been ſaid, ſerves firſt for refutation of thoſe that deny or corrupt the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine <note place="margin">Refutation.</note> of the Reſurrection of the body: The Philoſophers miſled by vain Philoſophy, were for the moſt part igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of, and Adverſaries to it <note n="a" place="margin">Et ut carnis Reſurrectio ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getur, de una omnium Philo ſophorum Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la ſumitur. <hi>Tertul.</hi> Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrip: adverſ. Heret.</note>; So were the Sadduces <note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 22. 23. Acts 23. 8.</note>; the firſt after Chriſt among the Chriſtians that denyed it, was <hi>Simon Magus</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiph. h.</hi> 21.</note>; ſome there were among the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> unſound herein <note n="d" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.</note>; as alſo <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 18.</note>; Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilides, <hi>Saturninus</hi> and many more are for this by <hi>Epiphani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Auguſtine,</hi> and other Fathers, condemned for Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks; many more might be named, were it neceſſary; I ſhall adde only one pair more of this viperous brood, <hi>Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pin</hi> and <hi>Quintin,</hi> whom in latter times about the year 1525. the Devil ſtirred up in <hi>Brabant</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne this and other precious truths of God, the latter ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving abjured his Hereſie, was for this and other notorious crimes, executed at <hi>Tourney</hi> in <hi>Gallick Flanders</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Gualter. Chronog.</note>: And if the ſame body riſe, then not an aerial and aetherial (as the Originiſts held,) nor (as <hi>Eutichius,</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> ſuppoſed) ſhall our bodies be impalpable, <note place="margin">Greg. l. 14. c. 29. in Job.</note> and more ſubtile then the Wind and Ayr; neither can the ſoul paſs out of one body into another in death; for either it muſt inform moe bodies then one, or ſome bodies muſt be joyned to other ſouls in the Reſurrection: We forbear to mention any more Hereſies or Hereticks; in this point, the Church hath been continually peſtered with them in all ages, ſo that it is no wonder, the grand Impoſtor hath in our times withdrawn ſo many from the ſimplicity of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>This ſhould be as a Bridle to reſtrain from ſin, and a <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 2. Exhortation.</note>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:117882:31"/>
ſpur to holineſs and vertue: <hi>Herein</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul) do I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe <note place="margin">Acts 24. 15.</note> my ſelf, to have alwayes a conſcienco void of offence toward God and toward men;</hi> then ſhall be a Reſurrection that men may be judged, and receive according to their deeds; what a madneſs thenis it for men to ſpend their days in vanity, as if no account were to be given? The Saints ſhall riſe to glory, they ſhall be as the Angels, then what manner of men ought they to be, who expect ſuch a Priviledge, as to be the children of the Reſurrection?</p>
            <p>And this ſhould be an encouragement to ſuffer chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully for Chriſt, ſith we ſhall have our reward in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the juſt; this was the Martyrs comfort and confidence in their ſufferings that they ſhould obtain a better Reſurrection <note n="g" place="margin">Heb. 11. 35.</note>.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, we ſhould with <hi>Job,</hi> earneſtly long, and patiently wait for this glorious change <note n="h" place="margin">Job 14. 14.</note>; with <hi>Paul,</hi> ſtrive to attain unto the Reſurrection of the dead <note n="i" place="margin">Phil. 3. 11.</note>; that is, that ſtate of perfection which doth accompany the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; we ſhould <hi>groan to be clothed upon with our houſe from Heaven</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 4.</note>; <hi>waiting for the Adoption, the Redemption of our body</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Rom. 8. 25.</note>.</p>
            <p>This alſo is a Fountain of Conſolation to the Saints,</p>
            <p n="1">1. In reſpect of death, we need not fear to dy, becauſe we hope to live again and in a far better condition; when we have put off our ordinary raggs, we ſhall be clothed with royal Robes; when our houſes of Clay are pulled down, we ſhall have a building raiſed of hewen ſtone; we leave a priſon, to poſſeſs a Palace; our vile bodies ſhall be made glorious: In the grave we reſt in our Chambers, and our duſt is living to the Lord: And concerning them that are aſleep, let us nor <hi>ſorrow as them which have no hope</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Theſ. 4.</note>, <hi>If ye love me</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>ye will rejoyce, becauſe I go to my Father</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Ioh. 14. 28.</note>: We ſhould rejoyce when our friends dy, for they go to our Father.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In reſpect of ſin, which cleaves ſo faſt unto, and ſo eaſily beſets us here, that we have cauſe to cry out with
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:117882:31"/>
               <hi>Paul, O miſerable man that I am, who ſhall deliver me from this body of death?</hi> In the reſurrection we ſhall be perfect as the Angels.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In reſpect of thoſe manifold wants, neceſſities, and afflictions we are ſubject to in this life: in the reſurrection all evils ſhall be removed, and all good things enjoyed, we ſhall be as the Angels of God, <hi>Jobs</hi> comfort was, That in his <note place="margin">Job 19. 26.</note> fleſh he ſhould ſee God; <hi>David's</hi> and Chriſts upon a like ground, <hi>Thou wilt ſhew me the path of life,</hi> the ſame was <note place="margin">Pſal. 16. 11.</note> the Martyrs conſolation. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks of times of refreſhing, <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 35.</note> which are a Chriſtians hope; and therefore we ſhould not <note place="margin">Acts 3. 19.</note> faint in affliction nor be diſcouraged with difficulties which moleſt us in our Chriſtian race: we ſhall have a time of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing at the appearing of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, to whom be glory and honour for ever and ever.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="conference">
            <head>
               <hi>A Conference between</hi> John Osborn <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpel, and</hi> Richard Coppin, <hi>concerning the reſurrection of the body.</hi>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oſb.</speaker>
               <p>JOb 19. 25. <hi>For I know that my Redeemer liveth, and that he ſhall ſtand at the latter day upon the earth. 26. And though after my skin worms de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy this body, yet in my ſleſh ſhall I ſee God. 27. Whom I ſhall ſee for my ſelf, and mine eyes ſhall behold, and not another, though my reins be conſumed within me.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>Job <hi>did not ſpeak as rightly he ſhould do, and that appears in</hi> chap. 42. <hi>where he comes to confeſs he ſpake things he underſtood not, here he gives an anſwer to thoſe words which he ſpake in</hi> chap. 19.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oſb.</speaker>
               <p>Whereas in your anſwer you affirm, out of <hi>ch.</hi> 42. that <hi>Job</hi> underſtood not what he ſpake; My reply is this.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Job</hi> ſaith not the things were falſe of which he here affirmeth he ſpake but underſtood not, but that he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood them not, which he afterward expreſſeth thus, <hi>things too wonderful for me, which I knew not,</hi> which by
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:117882:32"/>
any thing that yet appears by you alledged, cannot be drawn without violence and injury to the text unto any other ſence then this, he had ſpoken things, which for the nature of them, were ſo high, that he could not underſtand them; he could not reach them, or comprehend them, there was more in them then his underſtanding could attain unto: this doth not import a contrariety between his words and thoſe things he ſpeaks of, but onely a diſproportion of his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to comprehend them. A man may ſpeak of God and his ways as <hi>Job</hi> in this book doth, &amp; truly; and in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he may ſay, as <hi>Job, I uttered things I underſtood not, things too wonderful for me, which I knew not. For who can finde out the Almighty! how wonderful are his judgements, and his ways paſt finding out!</hi> So then the narrowneſs and ſhortneſs of <hi>Jobs</hi> underſtanding to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the Latitude, and reach the heighth of thoſe things which here he ſpeaks of, doth no whit overthrow the truth of that he had ſpoken concerning them. So that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the things were that <hi>Job</hi> intends in this 42 chap. which he underſtood not, when he uttered them, You muſt prove he ſpeaks falſly of them, which yet you have not done, nor can it with any good conſequence be gathered from the words alledged.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Though that were granted, and the words ſo taken, as by you they are urged, that he ſpake what he knew not, and beſide the truth, yet will not this ſerve your turn; he ſpeaks indefinitely, that he uttered things he underſtood and knew not, but that all the things he ſpake of were of that nature, and ſo falſly propunded by him, cannot be imagined, or affirmed with any pretence of reaſon; for then all that he ſpake muſt be falſe, which I think you dare not adventure to maintain; and if you ſhould, the very reading of his diſcourſe, without Argument, would refute you: if then it be onely ſome things he ſpeaks of you muſt clear the relation of theſe words in <hi>ch.</hi> 42. 3. to thoſe in <hi>ch.</hi> 19. of his Redeemer and Reſurrection, or by better evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:117882:32"/>
of Scripture or reaſon then yet you have produced, prove theſe to be of that ſort, or your ſilence would have been as argumentative as your allegation; and this you will hardly do, yea you muſt confeſs you cannot do it, if you do but examine, and acknowledge the teſtimony that God himſelf gives of <hi>Job,</hi> verſe 7 of this chapter; <hi>Ye have not ſpoken of me the thing that is right, as my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant Job hath.</hi> If Gods teſtimony deſerve the prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence (as doubtleſs it doth, as of one to whom all thoſe things that were to <hi>Job</hi> ſo wonderful and unſearchable lay open and plainly diſcernable) you muſt then prove this of his Redeemer, and Reſurrection by him after death, to be none of thoſe ſpeeches of his which are by God atteſted here to be right, or that all he ſpake of God was falſe, or let that anſwer fall, as having uttered things you underſtand not, things too wonderful for you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe words of God in commendation of</hi> Job, <hi>have reference to what</hi> Job <hi>ſaith in this 42 chapter,</hi> v. 3. 4, 5. <hi>ſpecially</hi> v. 5, 6. I have heard of thee by the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ear, but now mine eye ſeeth thee; wherefore I abhor my ſelf, and repent in duſt and aſhes. <hi>This is it the Lord commends</hi> Job <hi>for, as having ſpoken right con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning him.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oſb.</speaker>
               <p>This refers to other paſſages, for <hi>Job</hi> was ſet in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to his three friends, <hi>Job</hi> had diſcourſed with them, who are condemned by God as not having ſpoken right concerning him as <hi>Job,</hi> who is therefore commended; but they ſpeak not in this chapter, but before; therefore this te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony doth relate to things before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>Job <hi>ſo riſes that he knew not the time,</hi> Job <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in</hi> ch. 19. <hi>under the firſt Covenant, in</hi> 42 <hi>under the new, ſpeaking</hi> ch. 19. <hi>of his Reſurrection, and ſeeing his Redeemer, his apprehenſion being dark he could not tell whether it was in the body or ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oſb.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaketh not of Spirit, but of ſeeing God in his fleſh, which <hi>Job</hi> waited not for, but till after his body
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:117882:33"/>
had been deſtroyed with worms; and this <hi>Job</hi> calls the latter day.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>Job <hi>ſpake, that he ſhould ſee God at the laſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral day, but he was carnal, and his words were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed in this life; for he afterwards ſees him, he had a full ſight of God as he expected, and ſays I have ſeen the Lord already.</hi> I have heard of thee by the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ear, but now mine eye ſeeth thee, <hi>and that was the laſt day to him.</hi> Job <hi>ſpeaks, I have had thoughts that I ſhall ſee my redeemer at the latter day, but then</hi> Job <hi>was carnal; many ſouls will ſay, that, At the laſt day I ſhall ſee my Redeemer, as I have ſaid my ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oſb.</speaker>
               <p>Did <hi>Job</hi> conceive aright or not, when he ſaith, I ſhall ſee my Redeemer ſtand at the latter day upon the earth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>He was miſtaken as was</hi> Martha; Martha <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the reſurrection in one ſenſe, Chriſt in another.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oſb.</speaker>
               <p>This you have not proved, nor how this ſight of God which you ſay he had, was in his latter day.</p>
               <p n="1">1. When as you ſay it is in this life, you have not produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced any authority of Scripture to prove the latter day is ſo taken in reſpect of ſome latter part of the life of a man, but it is uſually taken for the latter part of the time of the worlds duration.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If it be elſwhere ſo taken, it doth not appear ſo taken in theſe words of <hi>Job,</hi> nay the contrary rather, for <hi>Job</hi> is ſaid to live one hundred and forty years after he had ſeen the Lord, and therefore<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it cannot be his latter day in this life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>It was the latter day to him.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oſb.</speaker>
               <p>He ſpeaks of ſuch a latter day that ſhould come after worms had deſtroyed his skin and his body, when his reins had been conſumed within him; therefore this latter day could not be in his natural life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>Job <hi>ſo ſpake of worms, that he ſhould ſee God after worms had deſtroyed his body, before he knew the ſight of God to be in this life; for he ſaid it one way,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:117882:33"/>
but found it another. As I my ſelf have thought, and as many other ſouls alſo. Now I appeal to the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of ſome that are here preſent whether it be not ſo.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oſb.</speaker>
               <p>Other mens ſayings or thoughts, prove not the truth of this; for men may miſ-conceive of truth: but did <hi>Job</hi> conceive aright, or did he not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>He was miſtaken, ſpeaking things he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood not.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oſb.</speaker>
               <p>Doth every man miſtake and ſpeak falſly when he ſpeaks of things he doth not underſtand? <hi>Job</hi> by Gods te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony is ſaid to ſpeak aright of God, yet queſtionleſs ſuch is the immenſity and perfection of God, that he could not comprehend him in his underſtanding: beſides, our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding or not underſtanding things we ſpeak of, doth not cauſe them ſo to be or not to be as we declare them: truth of what is ſpoken doth not depend on our conceptions, but on the proportion and congruity of the nature of thoſe things, and our expreſſions of them. Then did <hi>Job</hi> ſpeak truly or no?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>That he ſhall ſee God was true but the place and the time was not true: he ſpake not aright according to the time and place, onely as to the thing, that he ſhould ſee God was true, but that it ſhould be after he had laid down his body, that was not true: and accordingly he did ſee him, but in his natural life before he died.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oſb.</speaker>
               <p>That the ſight expected <hi>ch.</hi> 19. was accompliſhed before his death, you onely affirm, without one reaſon or Scripture to demonſtrate it; your bare aſſertion muſt be of no weight or conſideration with me, ſo long as I have the text ſo plainly and fully ſpeaking the contrary: let me hear what you can ſay to this, that <hi>Jobs</hi> ſight of his Redeemer was not expected to be accompliſhed until his skin and bones were deſtroyed with worms. What ſay you to this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>Job <hi>ſpake in relation to his ſeeing the Lord ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Reſurrection he then believed, which was in the body.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:117882:34"/>
Oſb.</speaker>
               <p>But how did <hi>Job</hi> ſee God after the deſtruction of the body, after the worms had eaten his body?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>Job <hi>had it not revealed to him the manner how, nor the time when.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oſb.</speaker>
               <p>Worms had not deſtroyed his body, therefore this could not be in his life time, but after death.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>Job <hi>did find this accompliſhed in his life time, becauſe he ſaw God.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oſb.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay, but prove not: let us proceed to the next Scripture.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Dan. 12. 2.</bibl> 
                  <hi>Many of them that ſleep in the duſt of the earth, ſhall awake, ſome to everlaſting life, and ſome to ſhame and everlaſting contempt.</hi>
               </q>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oſb.</speaker>
               <p>What ſay you to this Scripture? you cannot be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant that by ſleep in Scripture frequently death is meant; and that it muſt be ſo interpreted here, appears by this, that thoſe that are ſaid to awake, are ſaid to be in the duſt of the earth; and as by ſleeping we muſt underſtand their being dead, or continuing in the ſtate of the dead; ſo by waking is meant quickning, riſing to life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>By the duſt is meant the earth of mankind, or ignorance, in which his joyes and comforts lie hid and buried, from which he is ſaid to riſe, when theſe are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted to him; his ſleeping in the duſt is a mans carnal ignorant ſtate without the knowledge of God, or his joys and comforts, his awaking when he is changed, and God is made manifeſt, and appears in him.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oſb.</speaker>
               <p>It cannot be meant of riſing out of a carnall ſtate, or wherein a mans joys and comforts are buried; for ſome of thoſe that are ſaid here to awake, are ſaid to awake to ſhame and everlaſting contempt, which cannot be affirmed of thoſe that awake out of their natural and carnal ſtate, for they all awake to life everlaſting.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is meant of ariſing out of a carnall ſtate, the earth of mankind or ignorance, without the manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God; for ſo duſt ſignifies.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:117882:34"/>
Oſb.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt you muſt prove, that the duſt of the earth any where in Scripture ſignifies ſuch a ſtate of ignorance, a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſtate, without the manifeſtation of God.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that it is ſo taken in this place.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Man is ſaid to be duſt and aſhes.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oſb.</speaker>
               <p>But duſt here cannot ſignifie man, it is ſaid the duſt of the earth, and that many ſleep in the duſt of the earth: as that which is properly taken in one place, muſt not of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity be ſo taken in all places; ſo, that which is taken figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively in ſome places, cannot be admitted in the ſame ſence in others: Chriſt is ſaid to be a door and a Shepheard though he were neither in proper ſpeech: He is alſo ſaid to come as a thief in the night, which word ſometimes imports ſuch a one as comes to ſteal Cattel or other goods: becauſe theſe words carry a proper meaning in ſome Scriptures, muſt they therefore be of the ſame import in all? this were blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous againſt Chriſt, contrary to his nature and dignity: the ſame words are variouſly taken in divers Scriptures; ſo then, if the duſt of the earth do any where ſignifie ſuch a ſtate as you ſpeak of, yet that here it doth, you prove not. Your former Allegation, that ſayes, Man is duſt and aſhes, is little to the purpoſe; for here in <hi>Daniel,</hi> the duſt, and thoſe that ſleep in it, are diſtinguiſhed one from the other, but your interpretation confounds them. You ſay man is duſt and aſhes, and bring that as a parallel to this place, and withal grant as the Scripture ſayes, that many ſleep in the duſt, which in plainer Engliſh is thus, Many men that ſleep, ſleep in themſelves.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>True, for they ſleep in the old man.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oſb.</speaker>
               <p>I deſire you to prove your interpretation by the Scripture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is cleared by Eſay</hi> 26. 18. Thy dead men ſhal live, with my dead body ſhall they ariſe, awake and ſing ye that dwell in the duſt, &amp;c. <hi>Theſe Scriptures are compared together, by this I prove my interpretation, for I would have one Scripture interpret another.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:117882:35"/>
Osb.</speaker>
               <p>I am glad to hear your acknowledgment, that all interpretations of Scripture muſt be made good by Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; but you muſt know alſo, that in interpretation of Scripture, you muſt take ſuch for the eſtabliſhment of your ſenſe as are parallels, and have relation unto, or dependance upon one another; and that a word or phraſe may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken properly in one place and figuratively in another; and as for this 26. of <hi>Iſa. v.</hi> 17. you muſt prove that duſt is taken figuratively, for the ſtate of nature and ignorance; and dead men for thoſe that are in this ſtate: and when you have done this, you muſt alſo prove that agreement and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of this in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> with that in <hi>Daniel.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe Scriptures have relation to one another; and the earth here is the old man,</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>There is nothing of the old man, not one word in all this chapter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yes, v.</hi> 17. Like as a woman with child, that draweth near the time of her delivery, is in pain, and cryeth out in her pangs; ſo have we been in thy ſight, O Lord: <hi>v.</hi> 18. We have been with child, we have been in pain: <hi>that is, we have laboured and travelled to bring forth Chriſt in the ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>This you ſay, but you muſt alſo prove it; What is all this, <hi>v.</hi> 17, 18. to the old man, or labouring and travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to bring forth Chriſt in the ſpirit?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The bringing of the ſoul out of the duſt, is the bringing of the new man out of the old.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>Where is your proof that the bringing of the dead out of the duſt, is bringing the ſoul out of the duſt, and that, the bringing of the new man out of the old?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>This is proved v.</hi> 14. They are dead, they ſhall not live; they are deceaſed, they ſhall not riſe; therefore haſt thou viſited and deſtroyed them, and made all their memory to periſh.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>What is this to the old man?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>God's raiſing them, is raiſing their memory, or them
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:117882:35"/>
to a memory, which before they had not; it was a periſhing memory which before they had.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>What means the periſhing of their memory here?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>They remembred not God, or had not the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>Prove this phraſe to hold forth any ſuch thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The natural man is enmity with God.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>Prove the memory periſhing to be taken for natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſtate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is the darkneſs of their Underſtanding.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>Prove it is meant ſo here, and alledge your Scripture, and I will acknowledge my ſelf to be in an error.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I prove</hi> Ezek. 37. 11. Theſe bones are the whole Houſe of Iſrael; Behold, they ſay our bones are dryed up, and our hope is loſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>He ſays nothing of memory, much leſs of memory periſhing; but ſpeaks of hope loſt, which are two diſtinct things; hope being of things to come, and memory of things paſt; therefore this Scripture cannot witneſs for you, you muſt ſeek elſewhere.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Scripture carries it all along, that the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral mans memory periſheth not.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>I ſee little ſtrength or ſenſe in this anſwer, or that it is in any ſort pertinent to our queſtion; Let me now ſee how you can prove in this chapter, and particularly in this verſe he ſpeaketh of the new man; and that by duſt is meant corruption of nature, and darkneſs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>If men will not receive the truth, they may pick Cavils.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>You judge me, though judging be againſt your doctrine; but prove that by duſt is meant corruption and darkneſs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is it that awakens out of darkneſs? Chriſt in us who appears as dew on the herbs, till Christ as dew re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive our dead hopes; as appears alſo by</hi> Hoſ. 14. 51. I will be as the dew unto Iſrael, he ſhall grow as the Lilly:
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:117882:36"/>
                  <hi>How ſhall he fall as a dew, unleſs upon as as dead? Jeſus Chriſt is the dew, and he cometh not but on the dead.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>If this be granted, it doth but hold out this, that thoſe that are raiſed, are raiſed by this dew; but that the dead on which it falleth are ſouls onely, and not bodies, you have not proved.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>That coming is on a dry ſoul.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>Yet I deny that the ſoul only is quickned by Chriſt; I grant that Chriſt as dew and as rain falls on a withered ſoul and thereby quickens and revives it; but that it quickens the ſoul only, I deny, for it alſo quickens the body: of which he ſpeaks here in <hi>Iſaiah.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have proved the ſoul to be quickned by this dew; you muſt prove the dew doth deſcend upon the body alſo.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>It was rather my grant then your proof, that the ſoul is quickned; which we affirm alſo of the body; ſith what the dew is to the corn and graſs, that Chriſt is to the bodies of men; as the dew revives the corn and graſs, and makes it to flouriſh when it is dead and withered; ſo doth Chriſt raiſe mens bodies dead in the grave; which we having before abundantly proved by authority of Scripture, it is your part to diſprove, or ſhew the impertinency of the Scriptures alledged for, to the Propoſition by me main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Would you have me to prove all? Will you have no proof on your ſide? You will prove nothing.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>Seing you will have it ſo, we will make an Eſſay what may be proved out of this very verſe; from whence I doubt not to infer the verity of my Aſſertion, and the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of yours; and that he ſpeaks of bodies quickned by this dew, from a bodily death in the grave, rather then of ſouls from corruption; the dead that are here raiſed by the dew falling on them, are conformable to Chriſt; they are ſo dead as Chriſt's body was, and ſo raiſed as Chriſt's: <hi>Together with my dead body ſhall they ariſe;</hi> But Chriſt's Reſurrection was not from corruption and ſin, but from a bodily death to life; therefore ours alſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:117882:36"/>
Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſt did deſcend to the Nature of man, that is corruption; Chriſt muſt lay this in grave, and riſe from it.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>Then Chriſt was a ſinner.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>He took our ſins, and ſo his reſurrection was from ſin.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>Doth this of <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26. 17, hold out any ſuch thing? Yea, where is he ſaid to riſe from ſin?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop,</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>He took our Nature on him, and that's the cauſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>It was from the grave, and not from ſin, corruption, and ignorance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>If he roſe not from them, then he had them not.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>Neither had he, for he was without ſin: That re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains to be proved.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>He took all our infirmities on him.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>Not ſinful infirmities.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>All our infirmities, and bare our ſickneſſes.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>I deny that.</p>
            </sp>
            <p>
               <hi>John</hi> 11. 24.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>Let us go on to another Scripture, namely <hi>Joh. 11. 24. Martha ſaith unto him, I know that he ſhall riſe again in the Reſurrection at the laſt day. Lazarus</hi> was dead, lay four days in the grave, and ſtunk; yet of him <hi>Martha</hi> ſaith, He ſhould riſe again in the Reſurrection at the laſt day: This cannot be meant of any ſpiritual Reſurrection in this life, but of a Reſurrection after death: Which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of hers Chriſt confirms, by ſaying, <hi>I am the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>Martha <hi>ſpoke in Ignorance, and Chriſt by way of Reproof; Mark the words,</hi> I know (ſaith <hi>Martha)</hi> my Brother ſhall riſe again in the Reſurrection of the laſt day; <hi>Chriſt anſwers,</hi> I am the Reſurrection and the Life; He that believeth in me, though he were dead, yet ſhall he live: <hi>as if he had ſaid ſhe ſhould not believe her ſelf, but him:</hi> Martha <hi>believed not, as in v.</hi> 40. Said I not unto thee that if thou wouldeſt believe, thou ſhouldeſt ſee the glory of God? <hi>Therefore Chriſt reproved an Unbeliever.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:117882:37"/>
Osb.</speaker>
               <p>Chriſt inſtructs, reprooves not <hi>Martha,</hi> but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commends her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. <hi>John Hughes,</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Martha</hi> ſaith <hi>v.</hi> 27. that ſhe doth believe, therefore ſhe had faith.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>She believed in general, but not in particular, and who will not ſay, my friends that are dead, I ſhall ſee them again at the laſt day?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. <hi>Hughes,</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>You will not ſay it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. W.</speaker>
               <p>Bartholomew, Martha <hi>had external faith, but not internal faith.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yea, yea.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>Where do you prove by Scripture there is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal faith,? and what is external faith?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. W.</speaker>
               <p>Bartholomew, <hi>She heard with the ear, that was her faith.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>We deny hearing to be external faith.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. <hi>David Hughes,</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>V.</hi> 27. She makes profeſſion of her faith, ſhe ſaith unto him, <hi>Yea Lord, I believe that thou art the Chriſt, the Son of God, which ſhould come into the world.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. Barth.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I will prove the Divels had ſuch a faith; for they believe and tremble.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. <hi>Dav.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hughes, Martha</hi> ſpoke the ſame things which <hi>Peter</hi> did acknowledge, and had the ſame faith and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of <hi>Peter</hi> which Chriſt approves, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 16, 17. ſaying, <hi>Fleſh and blood hath not revealed theſe things unto thee.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>M. <hi>Coppin,</hi> When is the laſt day that <hi>Martha</hi> here ſpeaks of?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>When a man is converted, that is the last day; and when the old man is deſtroyed.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>Shew me a Scripture for that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>When he hath ſubdned all things, then is the laſt day.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>Then as long as any thing remains to be ſubdued, it is not the laſt day: <hi>Martha</hi> acknowledgeth her brother
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:117882:37"/>
ſhould ariſe at the laſt day, <hi>viz.</hi> when all things ſhould be ſubdued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>When all things appear to each man to be ſubdued, to him then is the laſt day come.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>You ſhould alſo prove as well as affirm this is the laſt day <hi>Martha</hi> ſpeaks of; If this be all you have to ſay, we will proceed on to the next Scripture.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>John</hi> 5. 28, 29.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>V, 28.</bibl> 
                     <hi>Marvel not at this, for the hour is coming wherein all that are in the graves ſhall hear his voice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>V. 29.</bibl>
                     <hi> And ſhall come forth, they that have done good, and they that have done evil unto the reſurrection of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>He ſpeaks of an hour to come wherein men ſhall be raiſed: The perſons to be raiſed, ſuch as are in the graves or ſepulchers, and ſuch as have done good and evil; and that they are raiſed to, or the conſequent of this reſurrection, is life to ſome, damnation to others; which cannot be meant of a reſurrection from ſin, corruption, or ignorance in a ſpiritual ſenſe; for none are ſo raiſed to damnation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>This is true, that it is to come, and ſo may this ſpiritual reſurrection be; Some at one time, ſome at another, have their reſurrection manifeſted to them.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>How come they out of their graves? You, muſt prove graves here to be ſin, corruption and ignorance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Examine</hi> Pſalm 88. 5. <hi>and ſee what</hi> David <hi>means by grave,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>V.</hi> 5. Free among the dead, and like the ſlain that ly in the grave, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>V.</hi> 6. Thou haſt laid me in the loweſt pit in the darkneſs, in the deeps.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>V.</hi> 7. Thy wrath lyeth hard upon me. <hi>And v. 7, 8, 9, 10, ſpecially v.</hi> 11. Shall thy loving kindneſs be declared in the grave, or thy faithfulneſs in deſtruction? <hi>All theſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſhew theſe to be corruption.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:117882:38"/>
Osb.</speaker>
               <p>Such a death, and ſuch a grave he ſpeaks of here, as in the reſt of the Pſalm; but <hi>v.</hi> 15. he ſhews it to be affliction; which ſo grievous, that he was ready to dy, or as one ready to dy: <hi>I am afflicted, and ready to dy, from my youth up; while I ſuffer thy terrors, I am diſtracted.</hi> He ſpeaks not of any ſpiritual death by reaſon of ſin, nothing of ſinfulneſs is mentioned in all this Pſalm; <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks only of an afflicted condition.</p>
               <p>Secondly, if this Pſalm were ſo to be underſtood, you muſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> make it appear that this Scripture doth apply, and properly anſwer the fift of <hi>John,</hi> and that the grave is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in <hi>John</hi> 5. 8. as it is here.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have proved it already, and therefore you muſt prove the contrary.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>By grave in <hi>John</hi> 5. is meant burial places; and Chriſt promiſeth a time ſhall come when the dead in them ſhall come out, ſome to joy, and ſome to torment.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R.</speaker>
               <p>Coppins brother, <hi>How do you prove the graves are taken for burying places?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>That is clear that the word ſo ſignifies, it is ſo in common uſe among us, that I need not ſpend time about that, and the Scripture alſo in other places uſes the word to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>By grave is meant the ſtate of ignorance, darkneſs, and corruption; and when Christ comes into the ſoul, then is the reſurrection; the grave is a death, a burial in ſin.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>In this ſpiritual Reſurrection from ſin and corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, all that riſe, riſe to life; but ſome in theſe graves riſe to damnation. But we will alſo leave this, and apply our ſelves to the next place; which is</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 24. 15.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And have hope towards God, which they themſelves alſo allow, that there ſhall be a reſurrection of the dead, both of the juſt and unjust.</hi> Here are two clear teſtimonies for the Reſurrection. 1. The object of <hi>Paul</hi>'s hope was the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the dead; but hope is of things to come:
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:117882:38"/>
                  <hi>Rom. 8. 24. But hope that is ſeen, is not hope; for what a man ſeeth, why doth he yet hope for?</hi> v. 25. <hi>But if we hope for that we ſee not, then do we with patience wait for it.</hi> The reſurrection then he hoped for, was a reſurrection to come; but that could not be from ſin, for that he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. 2. This reſurrection to come is of juſt and unjuſt men; and ſome are juſt, and others are unjuſt when they riſe; but in the reſurrection from ſin, all are juſt; none riſe from that, but thoſe that are juſt before God. The reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection he here ſpeaks of, preſuppoſeth the ſubjects; ſome of them, to be juſt before they riſe. The juſt are riſen al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready from ſin and corruption, yet ſhall have another reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, which can be no other then of the body, which they muſt have in common with the unjuſt; and not as a peculiar priviledge (any otherwiſe then for the manner and ends) or proper to themſelves.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>Paul <hi>having had the firſt reſurrection, expected a ſecond.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>But ſuch as unjuſt as well as juſt men ſhould have.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>This reſurrection was to be attained in his appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions, and ſo of the unjuſt alſo;</hi> Phil. 3. 10. That I may know him, and the Power of his Reſurrection; <hi>which he confeſſes he had not yet attained,</hi> v. 11, 12. <hi>in his appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions,</hi> but I follow after, if that I may apprehend that for which alſo I am apprehended of Chriſt Jeſus: <hi>v.</hi> 13. Brethren, I count not my ſelf to have apprehended; <hi>v.</hi> 14. I preſs towards the Mark. <hi>He preſſed forward towards his perfection, which is his ſecond reſurrection; for as ſoon as he apprehended he was riſen, he was riſen.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>R. Veyſey, Paul</hi> having enjoyed that reſurrection, which is the firſt reſurrection from Nature to Grace, doth yet ſay he deſires to attain to the reſurrection of the dead: Now <hi>Paul</hi> being once riſen, was no more dead in ſoul, therefore <hi>Paul</hi> expected a reſurrection of the body.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Though</hi> Paul <hi>was riſen in the firſt reſurrection, yet</hi> Paul <hi>was dead, becauſe he had not the ſecond.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:117882:39"/>
M. <hi>R. Veyſey,</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Then that reſurrection which is the firſt reſurrection, is but from one death to another, and ſo no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection at all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yes, becauſe as the ſtate of Nature is death in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the ſtate of grace, ſo is the ſtate of grace death in reſpect of glory.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. <hi>R. Veyſey,</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>How is that proved?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is proved</hi> in 1 Cor. 13. 9. and 15. 31. and 2 Cor. 4. 10.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>To your firſt place in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 9. I anſwer, mention is made of knowledge; we know in part; not a word of life or death. That of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 31. <hi>I dy dayly,</hi> will not argue the death of grace; he ſpeaks of his ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, which were ſo great, that he reckons himſelf as in a dying condition; and that in the 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 10. <hi>Alwaies bearing about in the body the dying of the Lord Jeſus, that the life alſo of Jeſus might be made manifeſt in our body:</hi> v. 11. <hi>For we which live, are alway delivered unto death for Jeſus ſake,</hi> &amp;c. This I ſay is of the ſame import, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their conformity to Chriſt in reſpect of afflictions, which only he cals death and dying, and not the ſtate of grace wherein they were; as is plain from, <hi>v.</hi> 8, 9. <hi>We are troubled on every ſide,</hi> &amp;c, ſo that theſe Scriptures make not for you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What ever is below the highest life, is death.</hi> Paul <hi>he knew that he had the life of Grace, yet he ſays that we are dead;</hi> Paul <hi>was dead according to the diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of Grace, in reſpect of the diſpenſation of Glory; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 31. I dy daily.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Osb.</speaker>
               <p>This is ſpoken of afflictions, and not of the ſtate of Grace, to ſhew it was a death in compariſon of Glory.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
